<!--
  ~ Copyright 2012 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='build_setup_plugin'>
    <title>Build Setup Plugin</title>

    <note>
        <para>
            The build setup plugin is currently <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link>. Please be aware that the DSL and other configuration may change in later Gradle versions.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>The Gradle build setup plugin prepares the current project for Gradle.
        Typically it will create the relevant build.gradle, settings.gradle files.
        If a <filename>pom.xml</filename> file is found in the project directory the Maven build is
        converted to a Gradle build. At the moment only the conversion from Maven 3 is supported.</para>
    <para>
        The plugin is currently <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link> which means it is already useful
        but not everything might work perfectly.
        The API, plugin and task names may change before the final release.
        Please let us know your feedback or report any issues.</para>
    <para>
        This plugin provides a lifecycle task named <literal>setupBuild</literal>.
        If a Gradle build with the task name <literal>setupBuild</literal> is triggered in a directory
        without an existing build file in the project directory, the build setup plugin is auto applied.
        This means that you can setup a Gradle project build without needing a stub build.gradle file declaring
        the build-setup plugin.

        If a pom.xml file is found in the project directory, a task of type <apilink class="org.gradle.buildsetup.tasks.ConvertMaven2Gradle"/>
        is added to the <literal>setupBuild</literal> lifecycle. Furthermore the <literal>setupBuild</literal> lifecycle task adds a dependency to the
        <literal>wrapper</literal> task which is implicitly added by the <xref linkend='wrapper_plugin'/>.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Tasks</title>
    <para>The build-setup plugin adds the following tasks to the project:</para>
            <table>
                <title>Build Setup plugin - tasks</title>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Task name</td>
                        <td>Depends on</td>
                        <td>Type</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <literal>buildSetup</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <literal>maven2Gradle</literal>, <literal>generateBuildFile</literal>, <literal>generateSettingsFile</literal>, <literal>wrapper</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td><apilink class="org.gradle.buildsetup.tasks.SetupBuild"/> - lifecycle task (no actions)</td>
                    <td>Generates a Gradle project.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <literal>maven2Gradle</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td>-</td>
                    <td><apilink class="org.gradle.buildsetup.tasks.ConvertMaven2Gradle"/></td>
                    <td>Converts a Maven project to a Gradle project by obtaining the effective POM. This task is only added if
                        a <literal>pom.xml</literal> file can be found in the project directory.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <literal>generateBuildFile</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td>-</td>
                    <td>
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.buildsetup.tasks.GenerateBuildFile"/>
                    </td>
                    <td>Generates an build.gradle file. This task is only added if no
                        <literal>pom.xml</literal> file can be found in the project directory.
                    </td>
                </tr>
				<tr>
                    <td>
                        <literal>generateSettingsFile</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td>-</td>
                    <td>
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.buildsetup.tasks.GenerateSettingsFile"/>
                    </td>
                    <td>Generates a <literal>settings.gradle</literal> file. This task is only added if no
                        <literal>pom.xml</literal> file can be found in the project directory.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <literal>wrapper</literal>
                    </td>
                    <td>-</td>
                    <td>
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.wrapper.Wrapper"/>
                    </td>
                    <td>Generates Gradle wrapper files.
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
    <para>
        The ConvertMaven2Gradle task works by obtaining the effective POM of the current project
        by executing Maven internally. Then it reads the dependencies and other information
        to generate build.gradle scripts. This task is inspired by the
        <ulink url="https://github.com/jbaruch/maven2gradle">maven2gradle tool</ulink>
        founded and maintained by recognized leaders of Gradle community;
        created by Baruch Sadogursky with contributions from Antony Stubbs, Matthew McCullough and others.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Maven conversion - features</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Uses effective POM and effective settings
            (support for POM inheritance, dependency management, properties)</listitem>
            <listitem>Supports both single module and multimodule projects.
                Generates settings.gradle for multimodule projects (*).</listitem>
            <listitem>Supports custom module names (that differ from directory names)</listitem>
            <listitem>Generates general metadata - id, description and version</listitem>
            <listitem>Applies maven, java and war plugins (as needed)</listitem>
            <listitem>Supports packaging war projects as jars if needed</listitem>
            <listitem>Generates dependencies (both external and inter-module)</listitem>
            <listitem>Generates download repositories (inc. local Maven repository)</listitem>
            <listitem>Adjusts java compiler settings</listitem>
            <listitem>Supports packaging of sources and tests</listitem>
            <listitem>Supports testng runner</listitem>
            <listitem>Generates global exclusions from Maven enforcer plugin settings</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            (*) - Note: Your project will be considered multi-module
            only if your reactor is also a parent of at least one of your modules.
            Why so? Reactor project is built last, when Parent project is built first.
            The reactor has to be built first, because effective-pom Mojo generates needed output
            only if it finds modules in first project it encounters.
            Making reactor also a parent achieves this.
        </para>

        <para>To convert a Maven project follow the steps:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Make sure your Maven project builds and uses maven3.</listitem>
            <listitem>Make sure no <literal>build.gradle</literal> file is available in your your Maven project folder.</listitem>
            <listitem>Run <code>gradle setupBuild</code> in your project directory.
                You should see that the <code>maven2Gradle</code> task is executed as a dependency on setupBuild.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Generate specific project types</title>
        <para>
            The build-setup plugin allows the generation of specific project types by passing the type via <literal>--type</literal> command-line option.
            For example generating a java library project you can run <code>gradle buildSetup --type java-library</code> in an empty directory.
            When passing a <literal>--type</literal> parameter to the <literal>buildSetup</literal> task, any pom file is ignored and the <literal>maven2Gradle</literal>
            task isn't part of the setup build.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>java-library</title>
            <para>The <literal>java-library</literal> build setup type generates
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>a <literal>build.gradle</literal>
                        file that that applies the Java plugin, adds mavenCentral() and the dependencies to allow testing with JUnit.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>the appropriate source directories, if they do not exist.</listitem>
                    <listitem>a sample class and a unit test, if there are no existing source or test files.</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
