<!--
  ~ Copyright 2010 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter id='cpp'>
    <title>C++ Support</title>

    <note>
        <para>
            The Gradle C++ support is currently <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link>. Please be aware that the DSL and other configuration may change in later Gradle versions.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        The C++ plugins add support for building software comprised of C++ source code, and managing the process of building “native” software in general.
        While many excellent build tools exist for this space of software development, Gradle offers C++ developers it's trademark power and flexibility
        together with the dependency management practices more traditionally found in the JVM development space.
    </para>
    <para>
        Gradle offers the ability to execute the same build using different tool chains. At present, you control which tool chain will be used to build
        by changing the operating system PATH to include the desired tool chain compiler. The following tool chains are supported:
    </para>
    <table>
        <thread>
            <tr><td>Operating System</td><td>Tool Chain</td><td>Notes</td></tr>
        </thread>
        <tr>
            <td>Linux</td><td><ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/">GCC</ulink></td><td>Tested with GCC 4.6.1 on Ubuntu 11.10</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Mac OS X</td><td><ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/">GCC</ulink></td><td>Tested with XCode 4.2.1 on OS X 10.7</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Windows</td><td><ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/visualstudio/en-us">Visual C++</ulink></td><td>Tested with Windows 7 and Visual C++ 2010</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Windows</td><td><ulink url="http://www.mingw.org/">MinGW</ulink></td><td>Tested with Windows 7 and MinGW 4.6.2. Note: G++ support is currently broken under cygwin</td>
        </tr>
    </table>
    <para>
        Currently, there is no direct support for creating multiple variants of the same binary (e.g. 32 bit vs. 64 bit) and there is no direct
        support for cross platform source configuration (à la <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/s/autoconf/">autoconf</ulink>) at this time. Support for different
        compiler chains, managing multiple variants and cross platform source configuration will be added over time, making Gradle a fully capable build tool for C++
        (and other “native” language) projects.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>
            Everything a build scripts DSLs, model elements and tasks used to manage C++ projects are added by the <literal>cpp</literal> plugin. However, it is typically
            more convenient to use either the <literal>cpp-lib</literal> or <literal>cpp-exe</literal> plugins that sit on top of the <literal>cpp</literal>
            plugin to pre-configure the project to build either a native library or executable respectively.
        </para>
        <sample id="useCppExePlugin" dir="cpp/dependencies" title="Using the 'cpp-exe' plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin-exe"/>
        </sample>
        <sample id="useCppLibPlugin" dir="cpp/dependencies" title="Using the 'cpp-lib' plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin-lib"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            The <literal>cpp-exe</literal> plugin configures the project to build a single executable,
            and the <literal>cpp-lib</literal> plugin configures the project to build a shared and static version of a single library.
        </para>
        <table>
            <thread>
                <tr><td>Plugin</td><td>Output</td><td>Task to create</td><td>Location of created binary</td></tr>
            </thread>
            <tr>
                <td>cpp-exe</td><td>Executable</td><td><literal>mainExecutable</literal></td><td><filename><replaceable>$buildDir</replaceable>/binaries/<replaceable>$project.name</replaceable></filename></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>cpp-lib</td><td>Shared Library</td><td><literal>mainSharedLibrary</literal></td><td><filename><replaceable>$buildDir</replaceable>/binaries/lib<replaceable>$project.name</replaceable>.so</filename></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>cpp-lib</td><td>Static Library</td><td><literal>mainStaticLibrary</literal></td><td><filename><replaceable>$buildDir</replaceable>/binaries/<replaceable>$project.name</replaceable>.a</filename></td>
            </tr>
        </table>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Source code locations</title>
        <para>
            Both plugins configure the project to look for <filename>.cpp</filename> and <filename>.c</filename> source files in <filename>src/main/cpp</filename> and use the <filename>src/main/headers</filename>
            directory as a header include root. For a library, the header files in <filename>src/main/headers</filename> are considered the “public” or “exported” headers.
            Header files that should not be exported (but are used internally) should be placed inside the <filename>src/main/cpp</filename> directory (though be aware that
            such header files should always be referenced in a manner relative to the file including them).
        </para>
        <para>
            The <literal>cpp</literal> plugin is also very flexible in where it looks for source and header files, and you can configure the above conventions to look however you like.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Building</title>
        <section>
            <title>Compiling on UNIX</title>
            <para>
                The UNIX C++ support is currently based on the <literal>g++</literal> tool which must be installed and on the <literal>PATH</literal>
                for the Gradle process.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Compiling on Windows</title>
            <para>
                The Windows C++ support can use either the MinGW <literal>g++</literal> or the Microsoft Visual C++ <literal>cl</literal> tool, either of which must be installed and on the
                <literal>PATH</literal> for the Gradle process. Gradle searches first for Microsoft Visual C++, and then MinGW.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Configuring the compiler</title>
        <para>Arbitrary arguments can be provided to the compiler by using the following syntax:</para>
        <sample id="gppArgs" dir="cpp/exe" title="Supplying arbitrary args to the compiler">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="args"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            The above example applies to the <literal>cpp-exe</literal> plugin, to supply arguments for the <literal>cpp-lib</literal> plugin replace
            “<literal>executables</literal>” with “<literal>libraries</literal>”.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Working with shared libraries</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>cpp-exe</literal> plugin provides an <literal>installMainExecutable</literal> task, which creates a development install of the executable, along with the shared libraries it requires.
            This allows you to run the executable without needing to install the shared libraries in their final locations.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Dependencies</title>
        <para>
            Dependencies for C++ projects are binary libraries that export header files. The header files are used during compilation, with the compiled
            binary dependency being used during the linking.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>External Dependencies</title>
            <para>
                External dependencies (i.e. from a repository, not a subproject) must be specified using the following syntax:
            </para>
            <sample id="gppArgs" dir="cpp/dependencies" title="Declaring dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="declaring-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
            <para>
                Each dependency must be specified with the <literal>dependency</literal> method as above and must be declared as part of the source set. The
                <literal>group</literal>, <literal>name</literal> and <literal>version</literal> arguments <emphasis>must</emphasis> be supplied.
            </para>
            <para>
                For each declared dependency, two actual dependencies are created. One with the classifier “<literal>headers</literal>” and extension
                “<literal>zip</literal>” which is a zip file of the exported headers, and another with the classifier “<literal>so</literal>” and extension
                “<literal>so</literal>” which is the compiled library binary to link against (which is supplied as a direct input to the g++ link operation).
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Project Dependencies</title>
            <para>
                The notation for project dependencies is slightly different.
            </para>
            <sample id="cppProjectDependencies" dir="cpp/exewithlib" title="Declaring project dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="project-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Publishing</title>
        <para>
            The <literal>cpp-exe</literal> and <literal>cpp-lib</literal> plugins configure their respective output binaries to be publishable as part of the
            <literal>archives</literal> configuration. To publish, simply configure the <literal>uploadArchives</literal> task as per usual.
        </para>
        <sample id="cppPublish" dir="cpp/dependencies" title="Uploading exe or lib">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="upload"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            The <literal>cpp-exe</literal> plugin publishes a single artifact with extension “<literal>exe</literal>”. The <literal>cpp-lib</literal> plugin
            publishes two artifacts; one with classifier “<literal>headers</literal>” and extension “<literal>zip</literal>”, and one with classifier
            “<literal>so</literal>” and extension “<literal>so</literal>” (which is the format used when consuming dependencies).
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                Currently, there is no support for publishing the dependencies of artifacts in POM or Ivy files. Future versions will support this.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>

</chapter>