<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="custom_plugins">
    <title>Writing Custom Plugins</title>

    <para>A Gradle plugin packages up reusable pieces of build logic, which can be used across many different
        projects and builds. Gradle allows you to implement your own custom plugins, so you can reuse your
        build logic, and share it with others.
    </para>

    <para>
        You can implement a custom plugin in any language you like, provided the implementation ends up compiled as
        bytecode. For the examples here, we are going to use Groovy as the implementation language. You could use
        Java or Scala instead, if you want.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Packaging a plugin</title>
        <para>There are several places where you can put the source for the plugin.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Build script</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can include the source for the plugin directly in the build script. This has the benefit that the plugin is
                        automatically compiled and included in the classpath of the build script without you having to do anything.
                        However, the plugin is not visible outside the build script, and so you cannot reuse the plugin
                        outside the build script it is defined in.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>buildSrc</filename> project</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can put the source for the plugin in the
                        <filename><replaceable>rootProjectDir</replaceable>/buildSrc/src/main/groovy</filename> directory.
                        Gradle will take care of compiling and testing the plugin and making it available on the
                        classpath of the build script. The plugin is visible to every build script used by the build.
                        However, it is not visible outside the build, and so you cannot reuse the plugin outside the
                        build it is defined in.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        See <xref linkend="organizing_build_logic"/> for more details about the <filename>buildSrc</filename>
                        project.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Standalone project</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can create a separate project for your plugin. This project produces and
                        publishes a JAR which you can then use in multiple builds and share with others. Generally, this JAR
                        might include some custom plugins, or bundle several related task classes into a single library. Or
                        some combination of the two.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para> In our examples, we will start with the plugin in the build script, to keep things simple.
            Then we will look at creating a standalone project.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Writing a simple plugin</title>
        <para>To create a custom plugin, you need to write an implementation of <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin"/>.
            Gradle instantiates the plugin and calls the plugin instance's <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin" method="apply"/> method when the
            plugin is used with a project. The project
            object is passed as a parameter, which the plugin can use to configure the project however it needs to.
            The following sample contains a greeting plugin, which adds a <literal>hello</literal> task to the project.
        </para>

        <sample id="customPlugin" dir="userguide/organizeBuildLogic/customPlugin" title="A custom plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q hello"/>
        </sample>

        <para>
            One thing to note is that a new instance of a given plugin is created for each project it is applied to.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Getting input from the build</title>
        <para>Most plugins need to obtain some configuration from the build script. One method for doing this is to use <firstterm>convention objects</firstterm>.
             The Gradle <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project"/> has a <apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.Convention"/> object 
             that helps keep track of all the settings and properties being passed to plugins. You can capture user input by telling
             the Project Convention about your plugin. To capture input, simply add a Java Bean compliant class into the Convention's list of 
             plugins. Groovy is a good language choice for a plugin because plain old Groovy objects contain all the getter and setter methods
             that a Java Bean requires. 
        </para>

        <para>Let's add a simple convention object to the project. Here we add a <literal>greeting</literal> property to the
            project, which allows you to configure the greeting.
        </para>

        <sample id="customPluginWithConvention" dir="userguide/organizeBuildLogic/customPluginWithConvention" title="A custom plugin convention">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q hello"/>
        </sample>

        <para>In this example, <classname>GreetingPluginConvention</classname> is a plain old Groovy object with a field called <literal>greeting</literal>.
            The convention object is added to the plugin list with the name <literal>greet</literal>. The name of the variable in
            the build needs to match the name of the field in the convention object.  The name you choose for your plugin 
            (<literal>greet</literal>) is arbitrary and can be whatever you choose. 
        </para>

        <para>Oftentimes, you have several related properties you need to specify on a single plugin. With Groovy plugins it is easy
            to offer a configuration closure block to group settings together. The following example shows you how to do this. 
        </para>

        <sample id="customPluginWithAdvancedConvention" dir="userguide/organizeBuildLogic/customPluginWithAdvancedConvention" title="A custom plugin with closure convention">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q hello"/>
        </sample>

        <para>In this example, several convention settings can be grouped together within the <literal>greet</literal> closure. 
            The name of the closure block in the build script (<literal>greet</literal>) needs a matching method on 
            the convention object, and that method must take a closure as an argument. Then, when the closure is executed, 
            the fields on the convention object will be mapped to the variables within the closure based on the standard
            Groovy closure delegate feature. This technique is possible in other JVM languages but may not be as convenient 
            as in Groovy. 
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>A standalone project</title>
        <para>Now we will move our plugin to a standalone project, so we can publish it and share it with others.
            This project is simply a Groovy project that produces a JAR containing the plugin classes.
            Here is a simple build script for the project. It applies the Groovy plugin, and adds the Gradle API
            as a compile-time dependency.
        </para>

        <sample id="customPluginStandalone" dir="customPlugin" title="A build for a custom plugin" includeLocation="true">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin"/>
        </sample>

	<para>
            So how does Gradle find the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin"/> implementation? The answer is you need to provide a properties file in the jar's
	    <filename>META-INF/gradle-plugins</filename> directory that matches the name of your plugin.
	</para>

        <sample id="customPluginStandalone" dir="customPlugin" title="Wiring for a custom plugin">
            <sourcefile file="src/main/resources/META-INF/gradle-plugins/greeting.properties"/>
        </sample>	

	<para>
	    Notice that the properties filename matches the plugin's name and is placed in the resources folder, and
	    that the <literal>implementation-class</literal> property identifies the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin"/> implementation class.
	</para>

        <section>
            <title>Using your plugin in another project</title>
            <para>To use a plugin in a build script, you need to add the plugin classes to the build script's classpath. To
                do this, you use a <literal>buildscript { }</literal> block, as described in <xref linkend="sec:external_dependencies"/>.
                The following example shows how you might do this when the JAR containing the plugin has been published
                to a local repository:
            </para>
            <sample id="customPluginStandalone" dir="customPlugin" title="Using a custom plugin in another project">
                <sourcefile file="usesCustomPlugin.gradle" snippet="use-plugin"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing tests for your plugin</title>
            <para>You can use the <apilink class="org.gradle.testfixtures.ProjectBuilder"/> class to create
                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project"/> instances to use when you test your plugin implementation.
            </para>
            <sample id="customPluginStandalone" dir="customPlugin" title="Testing a custom plugin">
                <sourcefile file="src/test/groovy/org/gradle/GreetingPluginTest.groovy" snippet="test-plugin"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Maintaining multiple domain objects</title>

        <para>Gradle provides some utility classes for maintaining collections of object, which work well with the Gradle build language.</para>

        <sample id="domainObjectContainer" dir="userguide/organizeBuildLogic/customPluginWithDomainObjectContainer" title="Managing domain objects">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q books"/>
        </sample>
    </section>
</chapter>
