<!--
  ~ Copyright 2010 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='gradle_wrapper'>
    <title>The Gradle Wrapper</title>
    <para>
        The Gradle Wrapper (henceforth referred to as the “wrapper) is the preferred way of starting a Gradle build. The wrapper
        is a batch script on Windows, and a shell script for other operating systems. When you start a Gradle build via the wrapper,
        Gradle will be automatically downloaded and used to run the build. 
    </para>
    <para>
        The wrapper is something you <emphasis>should</emphasis> check into version control. By distributing the wrapper with your project,
        anyone can work with it without needing to install Gradle beforehand. Even better, users of the build are guaranteed to use the 
        version of Gradle that the build was designed to work with. Of course, this is also great for 
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration">continuous integration</ulink> servers (i.e. servers that regularly
        build your project) as it requires no configuration on the server.
    </para>
    <para>
        You install the wrapper into your project by adding and configuring a <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.wrapper.Wrapper"/> 
        task in your build script, and then executing it.
    </para>
    <sample id="wrapperSimple" dir="userguide/wrapper/simple" title="Wrapper task">
        <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
    </sample>
    <para>
        After such an execution you find the following new or updated files in your project directory 
        (in case the default configuration of the wrapper task is used).
    </para>
    <sample id="wrapperSimple" dir="userguide/wrapper/simple" title="Wrapper generated files">
        <layout after="wrapper">
            gradlew
            gradlew.bat
            gradle/wrapper/gradle-wrapper.jar
            gradle/wrapper/gradle-wrapper.properties
        </layout>
    </sample>
    <para>
        All of these files <emphasis>should</emphasis> be submitted to your version control system. This only needs to be done once. After
        these files have been added to the project, the project should then be built with the added <command>gradlew</command> command.
        The <command>gradlew</command> command can be used <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> the same way as the <command>gradle</command> command.
    </para>
    <para>If you want to switch to a new version of Gradle you don't need to rerun the wrapper task. It is good enough
        to change the respective entry in the <literal>gradle-wrapper.properties</literal> file. But if there is for
        example an improvement in the gradle-wrapper functionality you need to regenerate the wrapper files.
    </para>
    <section id='sec:configuration'>
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <para>If you run Gradle with <command>gradlew</command>, the wrapper checks if a Gradle distribution for the wrapper
            is available. If not it tries to download it, otherwise it delegates to the <command>gradle</command>
            command of this distribution with all the arguments passed originally to the <command>gradlew</command>
            command.
        </para>
        <para>
            When you configure the <literal>Wrapper</literal> task, you can specify the Gradle version you wish to use. The <command>gradlew</command>
            command will download the appropriate distribution from the Gradle repository.
            Alternatively, you can specify the download URL of the Gradle distribution. The <command>gradlew</command> command will use this URL to download
            the distribution.
            If you specify neither a Gradle version or download URL, the <command>gradlew</command> command will by default download whichever version
            of Gradle was used to generate the wrapper files.
        </para>
        <para>For the details on how to configure the wrapper, see <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.wrapper.Wrapper"/>
        </para>
        <para>If you don't want any download to happen when your project is build via <command>gradlew</command>, simply add the Gradle
            distribution zip to your version control at the location specified by your wrapper configuration.
            A relative URL is supported - you can specify a distribution file relative to the location of <literal>gradle-wrapper.properties</literal> file.
        </para>
        <para>If you build via the wrapper, any existing Gradle distribution installed on the machine is ignored.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id='sec:unix_file_permissions'>
        <title>Unix file permissions</title>
        <para>The Wrapper task adds appropriate file permissions to allow the execution for the gradlew *NIX command.
            Subversion preserves this file permission. We are not sure how other version control systems deal with this.
            What should always work is to execute <literal>sh gradlew</literal>.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
