<!--
  ~ Copyright 2013 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='incremental_tasks'>
    <title>Incremental Tasks</title>
    <note>
        <para>
            Incremental Tasks are an <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link> feature.
        </para>
        <para>
            Since the introduction of the implementation described above (early in the Gradle 1.6 release cycle), discussions within the Gradle community have produced
            superior ideas for exposing the information about changes to task implementors to what is described below. As such, the API for this feature will almost certainly
            change in upcoming releases. However, please do experiment with the current implementation and share your experiences with the Gradle community.
        </para>
        <para>
            The feature incubation process, which is part of the Gradle feature lifecycle (see <xref linkend="feature_lifecycle"/>), exists for this purpose of ensuring high quality
            final implementation through incorporation of early user feedback.
        </para>
    </note>
    <para>
        With Gradle, it's very simple to implement a task that gets skipped when all of it's inputs and outputs are up to date (see <xref linkend="sec:up_to_date_checks"/>).
        However, there are times when only a few input files have changed since the last execution, and you'd like to avoid reprocessing all of the unchanged inputs.
        This can be particularly useful for a transformer task, that converts input files to output files on a 1:1 basis.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you'd like to optimise your build so that only out-of-date inputs are processed, you can do so with an <firstterm>incremental task</firstterm>.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Implementing an incremental task</title>
        <para>
            For a task to process inputs incrementally, that task must contain an <firstterm>incremental task action</firstterm>. This is a task action method that contains a
            single <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs"/> parameter, which indicates to Gradle that the action will process the changed inputs only.
        </para>
        <para>
            The incremental task action may supply an <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/> action for processing any input file that is out-of-date,
            and a <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/> action that executes for any input file that has been removed since the previous execution.
        </para>
        <sample id="taskDefinition" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Defining an incremental task action" includeLocation="true">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="incremental-task" />
        </sample>
        <para>
            For a simple transformer task like this, the task action simply needs to generate output files for any out-of-date inputs,
            and delete output files for any removed inputs.
        </para>
        <para>
            A task may only contain a single incremental task action.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Which inputs are considered out of date?</title>
        <para>
            When Gradle has history of a previous task execution, and the only changes to the task execution context since that execution are to input files,
            then Gradle is able to determine which input files need to be reprocessed by the task.
            In this case, the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/> action will be executed for any input file that was <emphasis>added</emphasis> or <emphasis>modified</emphasis>,
            and the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/> action will be executed for any <emphasis>removed</emphasis> input file.
        </para>
        <para>
            However, there are many cases where Gradle is unable to determine which input files need to be reprocessed. Examples include:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>There is no history available from a previous execution.</listitem>
            <listitem>You are building with a different version of Gradle. (Gradle does not use task history from a different version).</listitem>
            <listitem>An <literal>upToDateWhen</literal> criteria added to the task returns <literal>false</literal>.</listitem>
            <listitem>An input property has changed since the previous execution.</listitem>
            <listitem>One or more output files have changed since the previous execution.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            In any of these cases, Gradle will consider all of the input files to be <literal>outOfDate</literal>.
            The <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/> action will be executed for every input file, and the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/> action will not be executed at all.
        </para>
        <para>
            You can check if Gradle was able to determine the incremental changes to input files with <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="isIncremental"/>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>An incremental task in action</title>
        <para>
            Given the incremental task implementation <link linkend="taskDefinition">above</link>, we can explore the various change scenarios by example.
            Note that the various mutation tasks ('updateInputs', 'removeInput', etc) are only present for demonstration purposes: these would not normally be part of your build script.
        </para>
        <para>
            First, consider the <literal>IncrementalReverseTask</literal> executed against a set of inputs for the first time.
            In this case, all inputs will be considered "out of date":
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskFirstRun" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task for the first time">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="reverse"/>
            <layout after="originalInputs">
                build.gradle
                inputs/
                inputs/1.txt
                inputs/2.txt
                inputs/3.txt
            </layout>
            <output args="-q incrementalReverse" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            Naturally when the task is executed again with no changes, then task itself is up to date and no files are reported to the task action:
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskNoChange" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task with unchanged inputs">
            <test args="-q originalInputs incrementalReverse"/>
            <output args="-q incrementalReverse"/>
        </sample>

        <para>
            When an input file is modified in some way or a new input file is added, then re-executing the task results in those files being reported to <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/>:
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskUpdatedInputs" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task with updated input files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="updated-inputs" />
            <test args="-q originalInputs incrementalReverse"/>
            <output args="-q updateInputs incrementalReverse" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
        </sample>

        <para>
            When an existing input file is removed, then re-executing the task results that file being reported to <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/>:
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskRemovedInput" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task with an input file removed">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="removed-input" />
            <test args="-q originalInputs incrementalReverse"/>
            <output args="-q removeInput incrementalReverse" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
        </sample>

        <para>
            When an output file is deleted (or modified), then Gradle is unable to determine which input files are out of date.
            In this case, <emphasis>all</emphasis> input files are reported to the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/> action,
            and no input files are reported to the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/> action:
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskRemovedOutput" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task with an output file removed">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="removed-output" />
            <test args="-q originalInputs incrementalReverse"/>
            <output args="-q removeOutput incrementalReverse" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
        </sample>

        <para>
            When a task input property modified, Gradle is not able to determine how this property impacted the task outputs, so all input files are assumed to be out of date.
            So similar to the changed output file example, <emphasis>all</emphasis> input files are reported to
            the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="outOfDate"/> action,
            and no input files are reported to the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.incremental.IncrementalTaskInputs" method="removed"/> action:
        </para>
        <sample id="incrementalTaskChangedProperty" dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalTask" title="Running the incremental task with an input property changed">
            <test args="-q originalInputs incrementalReverse"/>
            <output args="-q -PtaskInputProperty=changed incrementalReverse" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
        </sample>
    </section>
 </chapter>