<!--
  ~ Copyright 2010 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>We would like to introduce Gradle to you, a build system that we think is a quantum leap for build technology
        in the Java (JVM) world. Gradle provides:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A very flexible general purpose build tool like Ant.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Switchable, build-by-convention frameworks a la Maven. But we never lock you in!
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Very powerful support for multi-project builds.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Very powerful dependency management (based on Apache Ivy).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Full support for your existing Maven or Ivy repository infrastructure.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Support for transitive dependency management without the need for remote repositories or
                <literal>pom.xml</literal> and <literal>ivy.xml</literal>
                files.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Ant tasks and builds as first class citizens.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Groovy</emphasis> build scripts.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A rich domain model for describing your build.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        In <xref linkend='overview'/> you will find a detailed overview of Gradle. Otherwise, the
        <link linkend="tutorials">tutorials</link> are waiting, have fun :)
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>About this user guide</title>
        <para>This user guide, like Gradle itself, is under very active development. Some parts of Gradle aren't
            documented as completely as they need to be. Some of the content presented won't be entirely clear or
            will assume that you know more about Gradle than you do. We need your help to improve this user
            guide. You can find out more about contributing to the documentation at the
            <ulink url="website:contributing.html">Gradle web site</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>You can find more examples, and some additions to this user guide, on the
            <ulink url="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/GRADLE/User+guide">wiki</ulink>.
            You can also contribute your own examples and extra content there.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
