<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='plugins'>
    <title>Gradle Plugins</title>
    <para>
        Gradle at its core intentionally provides very little for real world automation. All of the useful
        features, like the ability to compile Java code, are added by <emphasis>plugins</emphasis>.
        Plugins add new tasks (e.g. <apilink class='org.gradle.api.tasks.compile.JavaCompile'/>), domain objects (e.g.
        <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.SourceSet"/>), conventions (e.g. Java source is located at
        <literal>src/main/java</literal>) as well as extending core objects and objects from other plugins.
    </para>
    <para>
        In this chapter we discuss how to use plugins and the terminology and concepts surrounding plugins.
    </para>
    <section id="sec:what_plugins_do">
        <title>What plugins do</title>
        <para>
            Applying a plugin to a project allows the plugin to extend the project's capabilities. It can do things
            such as:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Extend the Gradle model (e.g. add new DSL elements that can be configured)</listitem>
            <listitem>Configure the project according to conventions (e.g. add new tasks or configure sensible defaults)</listitem>
            <listitem>Apply specific configuration (e.g. add organizational repositories or enforce standards)</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            By applying plugins, rather than adding logic to the project build script, we can reap a number of benefits.  Applying plugins:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Promotes reuse and reduces the overhead of maintaining similar logic across multiple projects</listitem>
            <listitem>Allows a higher degree of modularization, enhancing comprehensibility and organization</listitem>
            <listitem>Encapsulates imperative logic and allows build scripts to be as declarative as possible</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:types_of_plugins">
        <title>Types of plugins</title>
        <para>
            There are two general types of plugins in Gradle, <emphasis>script</emphasis> plugins and <emphasis>binary</emphasis> plugins.
            Script plugins are additional build scripts that further configure the build and usually implement a declarative approach to
            manipulating the build. They are typically used within a build although they can be externalized and accessed from a remote
            location. Binary plugins are classes that implement the <apilink class='org.gradle.api.Plugin'/> interface and adopt a programmatic
            approach to manipulating the build. Binary plugins can reside within a build script, within the project hierarchy or externally
            in a plugin jar.
        </para>
        <para>
            A plugin often starts out as a script plugin (because they are easy to write) and then, as the code becomes more valuable, it's
            migrated to a binary plugin that can be easily tested and shared between multiple projects or organizations.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:using_plugins">
        <title>Using plugins</title>
        <para>
            To use the build logic encapsulated in a plugin, Gradle needs to perform two steps. First, it needs to <emphasis>resolve</emphasis> the
            plugin, and then it needs to <emphasis>apply</emphasis> the plugin to the target, usually a <apilink class='org.gradle.api.Project'/>.
        </para>
        <para>
            <emphasis>Resolving</emphasis> a plugin means finding the correct version of the jar which contains a given plugin and adding it the
            script classpath. Once a plugin is resolved, its API can be used in a build script. Script plugins are self-resolving in that they are
            resolved from the specific file path or URL provided when applying them. Core binary plugins provided as part of the Gradle distribution
            are automatically resolved.
        </para>
        <para>
            <emphasis>Applying</emphasis> a plugin means actually executing the plugin's <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin" method="apply(T)"/>
            on the Project you want to enhance with the plugin. Applying plugins is <emphasis>idempotent</emphasis>. That is, you can safely apply
            any plugin multiple times without side effects.
        </para>
        <para>
            The most common use case for using a plugin is to both resolve the plugin and apply it to the current project. Since this is such a
            common use case, it's recommended that build authors use the <link linkend="sec:plugins_block">plugins DSL</link> to both resolve and
            apply plugins in one step. The feature is technically still incubating, but it works well, and should be used by most users.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:script_plugins">
        <title>Script plugins</title>
        <sample id="configureProjectUsingScript" dir="userguide/tutorial/configureProjectUsingScript" title="Applying a script plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            Script plugins are automatically resolved and can be applied from a script on the local filesystem or at a remote location.
            Filesystem locations are relative to the project directory, while remote script locations are specified with an HTTP URL.
            Multiple script plugins (of either form) can be applied to a given target.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:binary_plugins">
        <title>Binary plugins</title>
        <para>
            You apply plugins by their <emphasis>plugin id</emphasis>, which is a globally unique identifier, or name, for plugins.
            Core Gradle plugins are special in that they provide short names, such as <literal>'java'</literal> for the core
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.JavaPlugin" />. All other binary plugins must use the fully qualified form of
            the plugin id (e.g. <literal>com.github.foo.bar</literal>), although some legacy plugins may still utilize a short, unqualified
            form. Where you put the plugin id depends on whether you are using the <link linkend="sec:plugins_block">plugins DSL</link> or
            the <link linkend="sec:old_plugin_application">buildscript block.</link>
        </para>
        <section id="sec:binary_plugin_locations">
            <title>Locations of binary plugins</title>
            <para>
                A plugin is simply any class that implements the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Plugin" /> interface. Gradle provides
                the core plugins (e.g. <literal>JavaPlugin</literal>) as part of its distribution which means they are automatically resolved.
                However, non-core binary plugins need to be resolved before they can be applied. This can be achieved in a number of ways:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Including the plugin from the plugin portal or a
                    <link linkend="sec:custom_plugin_repositories">custom repository</link> using the plugins DSL
                    (see <xref linkend="sec:plugins_block" />).</listitem>
                <listitem>Including the plugin from an external jar defined as a buildscript dependency
                    (see <xref linkend="sec:applying_plugins_buildscript" />).</listitem>
                <listitem>Defining the plugin as a source file under the buildSrc directory in the project
                    (see <xref linkend="sec:build_sources"/>).</listitem>
                <listitem>Defining the plugin as an inline class declaration inside a build script.</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                For more on defining your own plugins, see <xref linkend="custom_plugins" />.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="sec:plugins_block">
            <title>Applying plugins with the plugins DSL</title>
            <note>
                <para>
                    The plugins DSL is currently <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link>.
                    Please be aware that the DSL and other configuration may change in later Gradle versions.
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>
                The new plugins DSL provides a succinct and convenient way to declare plugin dependencies. It works with the
                <ulink url="http://plugins.gradle.org">Gradle plugin portal</ulink> to provide easy access to both core and community
                plugins. The plugins DSL block configures an instance of <apilink class="org.gradle.plugin.use.PluginDependenciesSpec" />.
            </para>
            <para>
                To apply a core plugin, the short name can be used:
            </para>
            <sample id="useJavaPluginDSL" dir="plugins/dsl" title="Applying a core plugin">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin"/>
            </sample>
            <para>
                To apply a community plugin from the portal, the fully qualified plugin id must be used:
            </para>
            <sample id="useCommunityPluginDSL" dir="plugins/dsl" title="Applying a community plugin">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-community-plugin"/>
            </sample>
            <para>
                See <apilink class="org.gradle.plugin.use.PluginDependenciesSpec" /> for more information on using the Plugin DSL.
            </para>
            <section id="plugins_dsl_limitations">
                <title>Limitations of the plugins DSL</title>
                <para>
                    This way of adding plugins to a project is much more than a more convenient syntax. The plugins DSL is processed in a way which
                    allows Gradle to determine the plugins in use very early and very quickly. This allows Gradle to do smart things such as:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Optimize the loading and reuse of plugin classes.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Allow different plugins to use different versions of dependencies.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Provide editors detailed information about the potential properties and values in the buildscript for
                        editing assistance.</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    This requires that plugins be specified in a way that Gradle can easily and quickly extract, before executing the
                    rest of the build script. It also requires that the definition of plugins to use be somewhat static.
                </para>
                <para>
                    There are some key differences between the new plugin mechanism and the “traditional” <code>apply()</code> method
                    mechanism. There are also some constraints, some of which are temporary limitations while the mechanism is still
                    being developed and some are inherent to the new approach.
                </para>
                <section id="sec:constrained_syntax">
                    <title>Constrained Syntax</title>
                    <para>
                        The new <code>plugins {}</code> block does not support arbitrary Groovy code. It is constrained, in order to be idempotent
                        (produce the same result every time) and side effect free (safe for Gradle to execute at any time).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The form is:
                    </para>
                    <programlisting>
                        plugins {
                            id «plugin id» version «plugin version» [apply «false»]
                        }
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>
                        Where <literal>«plugin version»</literal> and <literal>«plugin id»</literal> must be constant, literal, strings and
                        the <literal>apply</literal> statement with a <literal>boolean</literal> can be used to disable the default behavior
                        of applying the plugin immediately (e.g. you want to apply it only in <literal>subprojects</literal>). No other statements
                        are allowed; their presence will cause a compilation error.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <code>plugins {}</code> block must also be a top level statement in the buildscript. It cannot be nested inside
                        another construct (e.g. an if-statement or for-loop).
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section id="sec:build_scripts_only">
                    <title>Can only be used in build scripts</title>
                    <para>
                        The <code>plugins {}</code> block can currently only be used in a project's build script. It cannot be used in
                        script plugins, the settings.gradle file or init scripts.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Future versions of Gradle will remove this restriction.</emphasis>
                    </para>
                </section>
                <para>
                    If the restrictions of the new syntax are prohibitive, the recommended approach is to apply plugins using the
                    <link linkend="sec:applying_plugins_buildscript">buildscript {} block</link>.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section id="sec:subprojects_plugins_dsl">
                <title>Applying plugins to subprojects</title>
                <para>
                    If you have a <link linkend="multi_project_builds">multi-project build</link>, you probably want to apply plugins to some or
                    all of the subprojects in your build, but not to the <literal>root</literal> or <literal>master</literal> project. The default
                    behavior of the <literal>plugins {}</literal> block is to immediately <literal>resolve</literal> <emphasis>and
                    <literal>apply</literal></emphasis> the plugins. But, you can use the <literal>apply false</literal> syntax to tell Gradle not
                    to apply the plugin to the current project and then use <literal>apply plugin: «plugin version»</literal> in the
                    <literal>subprojects</literal> block:
                </para>
                <sample id="pluginsOnSubprojects" dir="plugins/multiproject" title="Applying plugins only on certain subprojects.">
                    <sourcefile file="settings.gradle" snippet="include-subprojects" />
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="plugins-on-subprojects" />
                </sample>
                <para>
                    If you then run <literal>gradle hello</literal> you'll see that only the helloA and helloB subprojects had the hello plugin
                    applied.
                </para>
                <programlisting>
                    gradle/subprojects/docs/src/samples/plugins/multiproject $> gradle hello
                    Parallel execution is an incubating feature.
                    :helloA:hello
                    :helloB:hello
                    Hello!
                    Hello!

                    BUILD SUCCESSFUL
                </programlisting>
            </section>
            <section id="sec:custom_plugin_repositories">
                <title>Custom Plugin Repositories</title>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        The <code>pluginRepositories {}</code> DSL is currently <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link>.
                        Please be aware that the DSL and other configuration may change in later Gradle versions.
                    </para>
                </note>
                <para>
                    By default, the <code>plugins {}</code> DSL resolves plugins from the public <ulink url="https://plugins.gradle.org">Gradle Plugin Portal.</ulink>
                    Many build authors would also like to resolve plugins from private Maven or Ivy repositories because the plugins contain proprietary implementation
                    details, or just to have more control over what plugins are available to their builds.
                </para>
                <para>
                    To specify custom plugin repositories, add a <code>pluginRepositories {}</code> block to the <code>settings.gradle</code> file:
                </para>
                <sample id="customPluginRepositories" dir="plugins/consuming" title="Using plugins from custom plugin repositories.">
                    <sourcefile file="settings.gradle" snippet="custom-plugin-repositories" />
                </sample>
                <para>
                    This tells Gradle to first look in the Maven repository at <literal>maven-repo</literal> when resolving plugins and then to
                    check the Gradle Plugin Portal if the plugins are not found in the Maven repository. If you don't want the Gradle Plugin Portal to be searched,
                    omit the <code>gradlePluginPortal()</code> line. Finally, the Ivy repository at <literal>ivy-repo</literal> will be checked.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The <code>pluginRepositories {}</code> when in the <code>settings.gradle</code> file must be the first block in the file.
                    Custom Maven and Ivy plugin repositories must contain <link linkend="sec:plugin_markers">plugin marker artifacts</link> in addition to the artifacts
                    which actually implement the plugin. For more information on publishing plugins to custom repositories read <xref linkend="javaGradle_plugin" />.
                </para>
                <para>
                    It is also possible to add a custom plugin repositories using an <link linkend="init_scripts">Init Script</link> with
                    a <apilink class="org.gradle.api.invocation.Gradle" method="pluginRepositories"/> block. Plugin repositories added this way will be applied
                    before those in <code>settings.gradle</code>. Once a plugin is applied using the <code>plugins {}</code> DSL, you can no longer add custom
                    plugin repositories.
                </para>
                <para>
                    See <apilink class="org.gradle.plugin.repository.PluginRepositoriesSpec" /> for complete documentation for using the
                    <code>pluginRepositories {}</code> block.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section id="sec:plugin_markers">
                <title>Plugin Marker Artifacts</title>
                <para>
                    Since the <code>plugins {}</code> DSL block only allows for declaring plugins by their globally unique plugin <literal>id</literal> and
                    <literal>version</literal> properties, Gradle needs a way to look up the coordinates of the plugin implementation artifact. To do so,
                    Gradle will look for a Plugin Marker Artifact with the coordinates <literal>plugin.id:plugin.id.gradle.plugin:plugin.version</literal>.
                    This marker needs to have a dependency on the actual plugin implementation. Publishing these markers is automated by the
                    <link linkend="javaGradle_plugin">java-gradle-plugin</link>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    For example, the following complete sample from the <literal>sample-plugins</literal> project shows how to publish a
                    <literal>org.gradle.sample.hello</literal> plugin and a <literal>org.gradle.sample.goodbye</literal> plugin to both an Ivy and Maven repository
                    using the combination of the <link linkend="javaGradle_plugin">java-gradle-plugin</link>, the
                    <link linkend="publishing_maven">maven-publish</link> plugin, and the <link linkend="publishing_ivy">ivy-publish</link> plugin.
                </para>
                <sample id="completePluginPublishing" title="Complete Plugin Publishing Sample" dir="plugins/publishing">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="complete-plugin-publishing" />
                </sample>
                <para>
                    Running <literal>gradle publish</literal> in the sample directory causes the following repo layouts to exist:
                </para>
                <para>
                    <imagedata fileref="img/pluginMarkers.png" />
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="sec:old_plugin_application">
            <title>Legacy Plugin Application</title>
            <para>
                With the introduction of the <link linkend="sec:plugins_block">plugins DSL</link>, users should have little reason
                to use the legacy method of applying plugins. It is documented here in case a build author cannot use the plugins
                DSL due to restrictions in how it currently works.
            </para>
            <section id="sec:applying_binary_plugins">
                <title>Applying Binary Plugins</title>
                <sample id="useJavaPlugin" dir="java/quickstart" title="Applying a binary plugin">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin"/>
                </sample>
                <para>
                    Plugins can be applied using a <emphasis>plugin id</emphasis>. In the above case, we are
                    using the short name ‘<literal>java</literal>’ to apply the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.JavaPlugin" />.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Rather than using a plugin id, plugins can also be applied by simply specifying the class of the plugin:
                </para>
                <sample id="pluginIntro" dir="userguide/tutorial/pluginIntro" title="Applying a binary plugin by type">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="apply-by-type"/>
                </sample>
                <para>
                    The <literal>JavaPlugin</literal> symbol in the above sample refers to the the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.JavaPlugin"/>.
                    This class does not strictly need to be imported as the <literal>org.gradle.api.plugins</literal> package is automatically imported in all build scripts
                    (see <xref linkend='script-default-imports'/>). Furthermore, it is not necessary to append <literal>.class</literal> to identify a class literal in Groovy as it is in Java.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section id="sec:applying_plugins_buildscript">
                <title>Applying plugins with the buildscript block</title>
                <para>
                    Binary plugins that have been published as external jar files can be added to a project by adding the plugin to the
                    build script classpath and then applying the plugin.  External jars can be added to the build script classpath
                    using the <code>buildscript {}</code> block as described in <xref linkend="sec:build_script_external_dependencies" />.
                </para>
                <sample id="applyPluginBuildscript" dir="plugins/buildscript" title="Applying a plugin with the buildscript block">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="buildscript_block" />
                </sample>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:finding_community_plugins">
        <title>Finding community plugins</title>
        <para>
            Gradle has a vibrant community of plugin developers who contribute plugins for a wide variety of capabilities.
            The Gradle <ulink url="http://plugins.gradle.org">plugin portal</ulink> provides an interface for searching and
            exploring community plugins.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:more_on_plugins">
        <title>More on plugins</title>
        <para>
            This chapter aims to serve as an introduction to plugins and Gradle and the role they play. For more information on the inner workings
            of plugins, see <xref linkend="custom_plugins" />.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
