<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="scala_plugin" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>The Scala Plugin</title>

    <para>The Scala plugin extends the Java plugin to add support for Scala projects. It can deal with
        Scala code, mixed Scala and Java code, and even pure Java code (although we don't necessarily recommend to use it for the latter).
        The plugin supports <emphasis>joint compilation</emphasis>, which allows to freely mix and match Scala and Java code,
        with dependencies in both directions. For example, a Scala class can extend a Java class that in turn extends a Scala class.
        This makes it possible to use the best language for the job, and to rewrite any class in the other language if needed.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Usage</title>
        <para>To use the Scala plugin, include in your build script:</para>
        <sample id="useScalaPlugin" dir="scala/quickstart" title="Using the Scala plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-plugin"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Tasks</title>
        <para>The Scala plugin adds the following tasks to the project.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Scala plugin - tasks</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Task name</td>
                    <td>Depends on</td>
                    <td>Type</td>
                    <td>Description</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>compileScala</literal></td>
                <td><literal>compileJava</literal></td>
                <td><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.scala.ScalaCompile"/></td>
                <td>Compiles production Scala source files.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>compileTestScala</literal></td>
                <td><literal>compileTestJava</literal></td>
                <td><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.scala.ScalaCompile"/></td>
                <td>Compiles test Scala source files.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>compile<replaceable>SourceSet</replaceable>Scala</literal></td>
                <td><literal>compile<replaceable>SourceSet</replaceable>Java</literal></td>
                <td><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.scala.ScalaCompile"/></td>
                <td>Compiles the given source set's Scala source files.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>scaladoc</literal></td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.scala.ScalaDoc"/></td>
                <td>Generates API documentation for the production Scala source files.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <para>The Scala plugin adds the following dependencies to tasks added by the Java plugin.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Scala plugin - additional task dependencies</title>
            <thead>
                <td>Task name</td>
                <td>Depends on</td>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>classes</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <literal>compileScala</literal>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>testClasses</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <literal>compileTestScala</literal>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal><replaceable>sourceSet</replaceable>Classes</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <literal>compile<replaceable>SourceSet</replaceable>Scala</literal>
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <figure>
            <title>Scala plugin - tasks</title>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="img/scalaPluginTasks.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Project layout</title>
        <para>The Scala plugin assumes the project layout shown below.  All the Scala source directories can contain
            Scala <emphasis>and</emphasis> Java code. The Java source directories may only contain Java source code.
            None of these directories need to exist or have anything in them; the Scala plugin will simply compile
            whatever it finds.
        </para>
        <table id='scalalayout'>
            <title>Scala plugin - project layout</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Directory</td>
                    <td>Meaning</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <xi:include href="javaProjectMainLayout.xml"/>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <filename>src/main/scala</filename>
                </td>
                <td>Production Scala sources. May also contain Java sources for joint compilation.</td>
            </tr>
            <xi:include href="javaProjectTestLayout.xml"/>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <filename>src/test/scala</filename>
                </td>
                <td>Test Scala sources. May also contain Java sources for joint compilation.</td>
            </tr>
            <xi:include href="javaProjectGenericLayout.xml"/>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <filename>src/<replaceable>sourceSet</replaceable>/scala</filename>
                </td>
                <td>Scala sources for the given source set. May also contain Java sources for joint compilation.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>

        <section>
            <title>Changing the project layout</title>
            <para>Just like the Java plugin, the Scala plugin allows to configure custom locations for Scala production and test sources.</para>
            <sample id="customScalaSourceLayout" dir="scala/customizedLayout" title="Custom Scala source layout">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="custom-source-locations"/>
            </sample>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Dependency management</title>
        <para>
            Scala projects need to add a <literal>scala-library</literal> dependency to the appropriate configuration(s). This dependency will then
            be used as a compile and runtime dependency for the project's Scala code. It will also be used to infer a <literal>scala-compiler</literal>
            dependency for executing the Scala compiler and Scaladoc tool.
            <footnote>
                More precisely, if a <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> or <literal>ScalaDoc</literal> task's <literal>scalaClasspath</literal> is empty,
                and the project has at least one repository declared, the plugin searches the task's <literal>classpath</literal> for a
                <literal>scala-library</literal> artifact, and adds a corresponding <literal>scala-compiler</literal> repository dependency to the
                task's <literal>scalaClasspath</literal>.
            </footnote>
        </para>
        <para>
            If Scala is used for production code, the <literal>scala-library</literal> dependency should be added to the
            <literal>compile</literal> configuration:
        </para>
        <sample id="declareScalaDependency" dir="scala/quickstart" title="Declaring a Scala dependency for production code">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="scala-dependency"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            If Scala is only used for test code, the <literal>scala-library</literal> dependency should be added to the <literal>testCompile</literal>
            (but not the <literal>compile</literal>)
            configuration:
        </para>
        <sample id="declareScalaTestDependency" dir="userguide/scala/scalaDependency" title="Declaring a Scala dependency for test code">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="scala-test-dependency"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            In earlier Gradle versions, it was necessary to add a <literal>scala-compiler</literal> dependency to the <literal>scalaTools</literal>
            configuration. Although typically no longer necessary (because the compiler dependency is inferred), this is still supported for
            backwards compatibility.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Convention properties</title>
        <para>The Scala plugin does not add any convention properties to the project.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Source set properties</title>
        <para>The Scala plugin adds the following convention properties to each source set in the project. You can
            use these properties in your build script as though they were properties of the source set object (see
            <xref linkend="sub:more_about_convention_objects"/>).</para>
        <table>
            <title>Scala plugin - source set properties</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Property name</td>
                    <td>Type</td>
                    <td>Default value</td>
                    <td>Description</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>scala</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.SourceDirectorySet"/> (read-only)
                </td>
                <td>
                    Not null
                </td>
                <td>
                    The Scala source files of this source set. Contains all <filename>.scala</filename> and
                    <filename>.java</filename> files found in the Scala source directories, and excludes all other
                    types of files.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>scala.srcDirs</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <classname>Set&lt;File></classname>. Can set using anything described in <xref linkend="sec:specifying_multiple_files"/>.
                </td>
                <td>
                    <literal>[<replaceable>projectDir</replaceable>/src/<replaceable>name</replaceable>/scala]</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    The source directories containing the Scala source files of this source set. May also contain
                    Java source files for joint compilation.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>allScala</literal>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileTree"/> (read-only)
                </td>
                <td>
                    Not null
                </td>
                <td>
                    All Scala source files of this source set. Contains only the <filename>.scala</filename> files
                    found in the Scala source directories.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>

        <para>These convention properties are provided by a convention object of type <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.ScalaSourceSet"/>.</para>
        <para>The Scala plugin also modifies some source set properties:</para>
        <table>
            <title>Scala plugin - source set properties</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Property name</td>
                    <td>Change</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>allJava</literal>
                </td>
                <td>Adds all <filename>.java</filename> files found in the Scala source directories.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>
                    <literal>allSource</literal>
                </td>
                <td>Adds all source files found in the Scala source directories.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Fast Scala Compiler</title>
        <para>The Scala plugin includes support for <ulink url="http://www.scala-lang.org/docu/files/tools/fsc.html">fsc</ulink>,
            the Fast Scala Compiler. <literal>fsc</literal> runs in a separate daemon process and can speed up
            compilation significantly.
            <sample id="fsc" dir="scala/fsc" title="Enabling the Fast Scala Compiler">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-fsc"/>
            </sample>
            Note that <literal>fsc</literal> expects to be restarted whenever the <emphasis>contents</emphasis> of its
            compile class path change. (It does detect changes to the compile class path itself.) This makes it
            less suitable for multi-project builds.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Compiling in external process</title>
        <para>
            When <literal>scalaCompileOptions.fork</literal> is set to <literal>true</literal>, compilation will take place
            in an external process. The details of forking depend on which compiler is used. The Ant based compiler
            (<literal>scalaCompileOptions.useAnt = true</literal>) will fork a new process for every <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> task,
            and does not fork by default. The Zinc based compiler (<literal>scalaCompileOptions.useAnt = false</literal>) will leverage
            the Gradle compiler daemon, and does so by default.
        </para>
        <para>Memory settings for the external process default to the JVM's defaults. To adjust memory settings,
            configure <literal>scalaCompileOptions.forkOptions</literal> as needed:
            <sample id="zinc" dir="scala/zinc" title="Adjusting memory settings">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="adjust-memory"/>
            </sample>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Incremental compilation</title>
        <para>
            By compiling only classes whose source code has changed since the previous compilation, and classes affected by these changes,
            incremental compilation can significantly reduce Scala compilation time. It is particularly effective when frequently compiling
            small code increments, as is often done at development time.
        </para>

        <para>
            The Scala plugin now supports incremental compilation by integrating with <ulink url="https://github.com/typesafehub/zinc">Zinc</ulink>,
            a standalone version of <ulink url="https://github.com/harrah/xsbt">sbt</ulink>'s incremental Scala compiler. To switch the
            <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> task from the default Ant based compiler to the new Zinc based compiler, set
            <literal>scalaCompileOptions.useAnt</literal> to <literal>false</literal>:
            <sample id="zinc" dir="scala/zinc" title="Activating the Zinc based compiler">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use-zinc"/>
            </sample>
        </para>

        <para>
            Except where noted in the<ulink url="http://gradle.org/docs/current/dsl/org.gradle.api.tasks.scala.ScalaCompile.html">API documentation</ulink>,
            the Zinc based compiler supports exactly the same configuration options as the Ant based compiler. Note, however, that the Zinc compiler requires
            Java 6 or higher to run. This means that Gradle itself has to be run with Java 6 or higher.
        </para>

        <para>
            The Scala plugin adds a configuration named <literal>zinc</literal> to resolve the Zinc library and its dependencies. To override the
            Zinc version that Gradle uses by default, add an explicit Zinc dependency (for example <literal>zinc "com.typesafe.zinc:zinc:0.1.4"</literal>).
            Regardless of which Zinc version is used, Zinc will always use the Scala compiler found on the <literal>scalaTools</literal> configuration.
        </para>

        <para>
            Just like Gradle's Ant based compiler, the Zinc based compiler supports joint compilation of Java and Scala code. By default, all Java and Scala code
            under <literal>src/main/scala</literal> will participate in joint compilation. With the Zinc based compiler, even Java code will be compiled incrementally.
        </para>

        <para>
            Incremental compilation requires dependency analysis of the source code. The results of this analysis are stored in the file designated
            by <literal>scalaCompileOptions.incrementalOptions.analysisFile</literal> (which has a sensible default). In a multi-project build, analysis
            files are passed on to downstream <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> tasks to enable incremental compilation across project boundaries. For
            <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> tasks added by the Scala plugin, no configuration is necessary to make this work. For other
            <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> tasks, <literal>scalaCompileOptions.incrementalOptions.publishedCode</literal> needs to be configured to point
            to the classes folder or Jar archive by which the code is passed on to compile class paths of downstream <literal>ScalaCompile</literal> tasks.
            Note that if <literal>publishedCode</literal> is not set correctly, downstream tasks may not recompile code affected by upstream changes,
            leading to incorrect compilation results.
        </para>

        <para>
            Due to the overhead of dependency analysis, a clean compilation or a compilation after a larger code change may take longer than with the Ant based compiler.
            For CI builds and release builds, we currently recommend to use the Ant based compiler.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note that Zinc's Nailgun based daemon mode is not supported. Instead, we plan to enhance Gradle's own compiler daemon to stay alive across Gradle
            invocations, reusing the same Scala compiler. This is expected to yield another significant speedup for Scala compilation.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>