<!--
  ~ Copyright 2011 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="sonar_plugin">
    <title>The Sonar Runner Plugin</title>

    <para>The Sonar Runner plugin provides integration with <ulink url="http://www.sonarsource.org">Sonar</ulink>,
        a web-based platform for monitoring code quality. It is based on the <ulink url="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/SONAR/Analyzing+with+Sonar+Runner">Sonar Runner</ulink>,
        Sonar's client component that analyzes source code and build outputs and stores all collected information in the Sonar database. Compared to using
        the standalone Sonar Runner, the Sonar Runner plugin offers the following benefits:
    </para>
    <ul>
        <li>Automatic provisioning of the Sonar Runner. The ability to execute the Sonar Runner via a regular Gradle task makes it available anywhere Gradle is available
            (develeper build, CI server, etc.), without the need to download, setup, and maintain a Sonar Runner installation.</li>
        <li>Dynamic configuration of Sonar Runner from Gradle build scripts. All of Gradle's scripting features can be leveraged to configure Sonar Runner as needed.</li>
        <li>Extensive defaults for Sonar Runner configuration. Gradle already has much of the information needed for Sonar Runner to successfully analyze
        a project. By preconfiguring the Sonar Runner based on that information, the need for manual configuration is reduced significantly.</li>
    </ul>

    <section>
        <title>Plugin Status and Compatibility</title>
        <para>
            The Sonar Runner plugin is the successor to the Sonar plugin. It is currently in incubation. The plugin is based on Sonar Runner 2.0,
            which makes it compatible with Sonar 2.11 and higher. Unlike the Sonar plugin, the Sonar Runner plugin works fine with Sonar
            3.4 and higher.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Getting Started</title>
        <para>To get started, apply the Sonar Runner plugin to the project to be analyzed.</para>
        <sample id="quickstart" dir="sonarRunner/quickstart" title="Applying the Sonar Runner plugin">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="apply-plugin"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            Assuming a local Sonar server with out-of-the-box settings is up and running, no further mandatory configuration is required.
            Execute <code>gradle sonarRunner</code> and wait until the build has completed, then open the web page indicated
            at the bottom of the Sonar Runner output. You should now be able to browse the results of the analysis.
        </para>
        <para>
            Before executing the <code>sonarRunner</code> task, all tasks producing output to be analysed by Sonar need to be executed.
            Typically, these are compile tasks, test tasks, and code coverage tasks. In alignment with the Sonar Runner plugin's defaults (see below),
            the plugins adds a task dependency from <code>sonarRunner</code> on <code>test</code>. Further task dependencies can be added as needed.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <para>The plugin adds a <apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.sonar.runner.SonarRunner"/>sonarRunner</para> extension to the project,
        which allows to configure the Sonar Runner via key-value pairs known as Sonar properties. A typical base line configuration includes
        connection settings for the Sonar server and database.
        <sample id="quickstart" dir="sonarRunner/quickstart" title="Configuring Sonar connection settings">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="connection-settings"/>
        </sample>
        <para>
            Alternatively, Sonar properties can be set from the command line. See <xref linkend="sec:sonar_command_line_parameters" /> for more information.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Sonar Runner plugin provides good defaults for many standard Sonar properties. The properties and their defaults are summarized in the tables below.
            As can be seen, additional defaults are added for projects that have the <literal>java-base</literal> or <literal>java</literal> plugin applied. Note
            that Gradle doesn't add defaults for properties for which the Sonar Runner already provides suitable defaults (e.g. server and database connection settings).
        </para>
        <table>
            <title>Gradle defaults for standard Sonar properties</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Property</td>
                    <td>Gradle default</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.projectKey</td>
                <td>"$project.group:$project.path"</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.projectName</td>
                <td>project.name</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.projectDescription</td>
                <td>project.description</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.projectVersion</td>
                <td>sonar.version</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.projectBaseDir</td>
                <td>project.projectDir</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.working.directory</td>
                <td>"$project.buildDir/sonar"</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.dynamicAnalysis</td>
                <td>"reuseReports"</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>Additional defaults when <literal>java-base</literal> plugin is applied</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Property</td>
                    <td>Gradle default</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.java.source</td>
                <td>project.sourceCompatibility</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.java.target</td>
                <td>project.targetCompatibility</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>Additional defaults when <literal>java</literal> plugin is applied</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Property</td>
                    <td>Gradle default</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.sources</td>
                <td>sourceSets.main.allSource.srcDirs (filtered to only include existing directories)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.tests</td>
                <td>sourceSets.test.allSource.srcDirs (filtered to only include existing directories)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.binaries</td>
                <td>sourceSets.main.runtimeClasspath (filtered to only include directories)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.libraries</td>
                <td>sourceSets.main.runtimeClasspath (filtering to only include files; {@code rt.jar} added if necessary)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>sonar.surefire.reportsPath</td>
                <td>test.testResultsDir (if the directory exists)</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
        <para>
            For a definitive list of standard Sonar properties, consult the <ulink url="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/SONAR/Analysis+Parameters">Sonar documentation</ulink>.
            If you happen to use additional Sonar plugins, consult their documentation.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Analyzing Multi-Project Builds</title>
        <para>The Sonar Runner is capable of analyzing whole project hierarchies at once. This yields a hierarchical view in the
            Sonar web interface, with aggregated metrics and the ability to drill down into subprojects. Analyzing a project hierarchy
            is also faster than analyzing each project separately.
        </para>
        <para>
            To analyze a project hierarchy, apply the Sonar Runner plugin to the root project of the hierarchy.
            Typically (but not necessarily) this will be the root project of the Gradle build. Information pertaining to the
            whole analysis, like server and database connections settings, have to be configured in the <literal>sonarRunner</literal>
            block of the root project. Project-specific information is configured in the <literal>sonarRunner</literal> block
            of the corresponding project. Note that Sonar properties set on the command line always apply to the root project.
        </para>
        <para>
            The exclude selected subprojects from being analyzed, set <code>sonarRunner.skipProject</code> to <code>true</code>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Analyzing Custom Source Sets</title>
        <para>By default, the Sonar Runner plugin will analyze the production sources in the project's <literal>main</literal> source set, and
            the test sources in the project's <literal>test</literal> source set. This works independently of the project's source directory layout.
            Additional source sets can be added as needed.
        </para>
        <sample id="advanced" dir="sonar/advanced" title="Analyzing custom source sets">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="source-sets"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Analyzing languages other than Java</title>
        <para>
            To analyze code written in a language other than Java, install the corresponding
            <ulink url="http://www.sonarsource.com/products/plugins/languages/">Sonar plugin</ulink>, and set
            <literal>sonar.project.language</literal> accordingly:
        </para>
        <sample id="advanced" dir="sonar/advanced" title="Analyzing languages other than Java">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="languages" />
        </sample>
        <para>
            As of Sonar 3.4, only one language per project can be analyzed. You can, however, set a different language for each project in a
            multi-project build.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Advanced Configuration</title>
        <para>
            Let's have a closer look at the <code>sonarRunner.sonarProperties {}</code> block. TODO
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:sonar_command_line_parameters">
        <title>Configuring Sonar Properties from the Command Line</title>
        <para>
            Sonar Properties can also be set from the command line, by setting a system property named exactly like the Sonar property in question.
            This can be useful when dealing with sensitive information (e.g. credentials), environment information, or for ad-hoc configuration.
            <code>
                gradle sonarRunner -Dsonar.host.url=http://sonar.mycompany.com -Dsonar.jdbc.password=myPassword -Dsonar.verbose=true
            </code>
            While certainly useful at times, we do recommend to keep the bulk of the configuration in a (versioned) build script, readily accessible to everyone.
        </para>
        <para>A Sonar property value set via a system property overrides any value set in a build script (for the same property). When
            analyzing a project hierarchy, values set via system properties apply to the root project of the analyzed hierarchy.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Executing Sonar Runner in a separate process</title>
        <para>
            Depending on project size, the Sonar Runner may require a lot of memory. For this and other (e.g. isolation) reasons,
            it is desirable to execute the Sonar Runner in a separate process. This feature will be provided once Sonar Runner 2.1
            has been released and adopted by the Sonar Runner plugin. Until then, the Sonar Runner is executed in the
            main Gradle process. See <xref linkend="sec:gradle_configuration_properties"/> for how to manage memory settings for that process.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Tasks</title>
        <para>The Sonar Runner plugin adds the following tasks to the project.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Sonar Runner plugin - tasks</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Task name</td>
                    <td>Depends on</td>
                    <td>Type</td>
                    <td>Description</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>sonarRunner</literal></td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td><apilink class="org.gradle.api.plugins.sonar.runner.SonarRunner"/></td>
                <td>Analyzes a project hierarchy and stores the results in the Sonar database.</td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>
</chapter>