<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='more_about_tasks'>
    <title>More about Tasks</title>
    <para>In the introductory tutorial (<xref linkend='tutorial_using_tasks'/>) you learned how to
        create simple tasks. You also learned how to add additional behavior to these tasks later on, and you
        learned how to create dependencies between tasks. This was all about simple tasks, but Gradle takes the concept
        of tasks further. Gradle supports <firstterm>enhanced tasks</firstterm>, which are tasks that have their own
        properties and methods. This is really different from what you are used to with Ant targets. Such enhanced tasks are
        either provided by you or built into Gradle.
    </para>
    <section id="sec:task_outcomes">
        <title>Task outcomes</title>
        <para>
            When Gradle executes a task, it can label the task with different outcomes in the console UI and via the Tooling API (see <xref linkend="embedding"/>).
            These labels are based on if a task has actions to execute, if it should execute those actions, if it did execute those actions and if those actions made any changes.
        </para>
        <table>
            <title>Details about task outcomes</title>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Outcome label</th>
                    <th>Description of outcome</th>
                    <th>Situations that have this outcome</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>(no label)</literal> or <literal>EXECUTED</literal></td>
                <td>Task executed its actions.</td>
                <td>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Used whenever a task has actions and Gradle has determined they should be executed as part of a build.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Used whenever a task has no actions and some dependencies, and any of the dependencies are executed. See also <xref linkend="sec:lifecycle_tasks"/>.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>UP-TO-DATE</literal></td>
                <td>Task's outputs did not change.</td>
                <td>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has outputs and inputs and they have not changed. See <xref linkend="sec:up_to_date_checks"/>.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has actions, but the task tells Gradle it did not change its outputs.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has no actions and some dependencies, but all of the dependencies are up-to-date, skipped or from cache. See also <xref linkend="sec:lifecycle_tasks"/>.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has no actions and no dependencies.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>FROM-CACHE</literal></td>
                <td>Task's outputs could be found from a previous execution.</td>
                <td>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has outputs restored from the build cache. See <xref linkend="build_cache"/>.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>SKIPPED</literal></td>
                <td>Task did not execute its actions.</td>
                <td>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has been explicitly excluded from the command-line. See <xref linkend="sec:excluding_tasks_from_the_command_line"/>.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has an <literal>onlyIf</literal> predicate return false. See <xref linkend="sec:using_a_predicate"/>.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><literal>NO-SOURCE</literal></td>
                <td>Task did not need to execute its actions.</td>
                <td>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Used when a task has inputs and outputs, but <link linkend="skip-when-empty">no sources</link>. For example, source files are <literal>.java</literal> files for <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.compile.JavaCompile"/>.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:defining_tasks">
        <title>Defining tasks</title>
        <para>We have already seen how to define tasks using a keyword style in <xref linkend="tutorial_using_tasks"/>.
            There are a few variations on this style, which you may need to use in certain situations. For example,
            the keyword style does not work in expressions.
        </para>
        <sample id="defineAsExpression" dir="userguide/tasks/defineAsExpression" title="Defining tasks">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>You can also use strings for the task names:</para>
        <sample id="defineUsingStringTaskNames" dir="userguide/tasks/defineUsingStringTaskNames" title="Defining tasks - using strings for task names">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>There is an alternative syntax for defining tasks, which you may prefer to use:</para>
        <sample id="addToTaskContainer" dir="userguide/tasks/addToTaskContainer" title="Defining tasks with alternative syntax">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Here we add tasks to the <literal>tasks</literal> collection. Have a look at
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskContainer"/> for more variations of the <literal>create()</literal>
            method.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:locating_tasks">
        <title>Locating tasks</title>
        <para>You often need to locate the tasks that you have defined in the build file, for example, to configure them
            or use them for dependencies. There are a number of ways of doing this. Firstly, each task is available as
            a property of the project, using the task name as the property name:
        </para>
        <sample id="accessAsProperty" dir="userguide/tasks/accessAsProperty" title="Accessing tasks as properties">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Tasks are also available through the <literal>tasks</literal> collection.</para>
        <sample id="accessFromTaskContainer" dir="userguide/tasks/accessFromTaskContainer" title="Accessing tasks via tasks collection">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>You can access tasks from any project using the task's path using the <literal>tasks.getByPath()</literal>
            method. You can call the <literal>getByPath()</literal> method with a task name, or a relative path, or an
            absolute path.</para>
        <sample id="accessUsingPath" dir="userguide/tasks/accessUsingPath" title="Accessing tasks by path">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q hello"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Have a look at <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskContainer"/> for more options for locating tasks.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:configuring_tasks">
        <title>Configuring tasks</title>
        <para>As an example, let's look at the <classname>Copy</classname> task provided by Gradle. To create a
            <classname>Copy</classname> task for your build, you can declare in your build script:
        </para>
        <sample id="declareTask" dir="userguide/tasks/configureUsingClosure" title="Creating a copy task">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="declare-task"/>
        </sample>
        <para>This creates a copy task with no default behavior.
            The task can be configured using its API (see <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Copy"/>).
			The following examples show several different ways to achieve the same configuration.
        </para>
        <para>Just to be clear, realize that the name of this task is “<literal>myCopy</literal>”, but it is of
        <emphasis>type</emphasis> “<literal>Copy</literal>”.  You can have multiple tasks of the same
        <emphasis>type</emphasis>, but with different names. You'll find this gives you a lot of power to implement
        cross-cutting concerns across all tasks of a particular type.
        </para>
        <sample id="configureUsingVar" dir="userguide/tasks/configureUsingVar" title="Configuring a task - various ways">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>This is similar to the way we would configure objects in Java. You have to repeat the context
            (<literal>myCopy</literal>) in the configuration statement every time. This is a redundancy and not very
            nice to read.
        </para>
        <para>There is another way of configuring a task. It also preserves the context and it is arguably the
            most readable. It is usually our favorite.
        </para>
        <sample id="configureUsingClosure" dir="userguide/tasks/configureUsingClosure" title="Configuring a task - with closure">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>This works for <emphasis>any</emphasis> task. Line 3 of the example is just a shortcut for the
            <literal>tasks.getByName()</literal> method. It is important to note that if you pass a closure to the
            <literal>getByName()</literal> method, this closure is applied to <emphasis>configure</emphasis> the task, not when
            the task executes.
        </para>
        <para>You can also use a configuration closure when you define a task.</para>
        <sample id="defineAndConfigure" dir="userguide/tasks/defineAndConfigure" title="Defining a task with closure">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="no-description"/>
        </sample>
        <tip>
            <title>Don't forget about the build phases</title>
            <para>A task has both configuration and actions.
                When using the <literal>&lt;&lt;</literal>, you are simply using a shortcut to define an action.
                Code defined in the configuration section of your task will get executed during the configuration phase of the build regardless of what task was targeted.
                See <xref linkend="build_lifecycle"/> for more details about the build lifecycle.
            </para>
        </tip>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:adding_dependencies_to_tasks">
        <title>Adding dependencies to a task</title>
        <para>There are several ways you can define the dependencies of a task. In
            <xref linkend='sec:task_dependencies'/>
            you were introduced to defining dependencies using task names. Task names can refer to tasks in the same
            project as the task, or to tasks in other projects. To refer to a task in another project, you prefix the
            name of the task with the path of the project it belongs to. The following is an example which adds a dependency
            from
            <literal>projectA:taskX</literal>
            to
            <literal>projectB:taskY</literal>:
        </para>
        <sample id="addDependencyUsingPath" dir="userguide/tasks/addDependencyUsingPath" title="Adding dependency on task from another project">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Instead of using a task name, you can define a dependency using a
            <classname>Task</classname> object, as shown in this example:
        </para>
        <sample id="addDependencyUsingTask" dir="userguide/tasks/addDependencyUsingTask" title="Adding dependency using task object">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>For more advanced uses, you can define a task dependency using a closure. When evaluated, the closure is
            passed the task whose dependencies are being calculated. The closure should return a single
            <classname>Task</classname> or collection of <classname>Task</classname> objects, which are then treated
            as dependencies of the task. The following example adds a dependency from <literal>taskX</literal>
            to all the tasks in the project whose name starts with <literal>lib</literal>:
        </para>
        <sample id="addDependencyUsingClosure" dir="userguide/tasks/addDependencyUsingClosure" title="Adding dependency using closure">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>For more information about task dependencies, see the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task"/> API.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:ordering_tasks">
        <title>Ordering tasks</title>
        <note>
            <para>
                Task ordering is an <link linkend="feature_lifecycle">incubating</link> feature. Please be aware that this feature may change in later Gradle versions.
            </para>
        </note>
        <para>
            In some cases it is useful to control the <emphasis>order</emphasis> in which 2 tasks will execute, without introducing an explicit dependency between those tasks.
            The primary difference between a task <emphasis>ordering</emphasis> and a task <emphasis>dependency</emphasis> is that an ordering rule does not influence which tasks
            will be executed, only the order in which they will be executed.
        </para>
        <para>
            Task ordering can be useful in a number of scenarios:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Enforce sequential ordering of tasks: e.g. 'build' never runs before 'clean'.</listitem>
            <listitem>Run build validations early in the build: e.g. validate I have the correct credentials before starting the work for a release build.</listitem>
            <listitem>Get feedback faster by running quick verification tasks before long verification tasks: e.g. unit tests should run before integration tests.</listitem>
            <listitem>A task that aggregates the results of all tasks of a particular type: e.g. test report task combines the outputs of all executed test tasks.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            There are two ordering rules available: “<emphasis>must run after</emphasis>” and “<emphasis>should run after</emphasis>”.
        </para>
        <para>When you use the “must run after” ordering rule you specify that <literal>taskB</literal> must always
        run after <literal>taskA</literal>, whenever both <literal>taskA</literal> and <literal>taskB</literal> will
        be run. This is expressed as <literal>taskB.mustRunAfter(taskA)</literal>. The “should run
        after” ordering rule is similar but less strict as it will be ignored in two situations. Firstly if using
        that rule introduces an ordering cycle. Secondly when using parallel execution and all dependencies of a
        task have been satisfied apart from the “should run after” task, then this task will be run regardless of
        whether its “should run after” dependencies have been run or not. You should use “should run after”
        where the ordering is helpful but not strictly required.
        </para>
        <para>
            With these rules present it is still possible to execute <literal>taskA</literal> without <literal>taskB</literal> and vice-versa.
        </para>
        <sample id="mustRunAfter" dir="userguide/tasks/mustRunAfter" title="Adding a 'must run after' task ordering">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskY taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <sample id="shouldRunAfter" dir="userguide/tasks/shouldRunAfter" title="Adding a 'should run after' task ordering">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskY taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>In the examples above, it is still possible to execute <literal>taskY</literal> without causing <literal>taskX</literal> to run:</para>
        <sample id="mustRunAfterSingleTask" dir="userguide/tasks/mustRunAfter" title="Task ordering does not imply task execution">
            <output args="-q taskY"/>
        </sample>
        <para>To specify a “must run after” or “should run after” ordering between 2 tasks, you use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="mustRunAfter"/> and <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="shouldRunAfter"/> methods.
            These methods accept a task instance, a task name or any other input accepted by <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="dependsOn"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Note that “<literal>B.mustRunAfter(A)</literal>” or “<literal>B.shouldRunAfter(A)</literal>” does not imply any execution dependency between the tasks:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>It is possible to execute tasks <literal>A</literal> and <literal>B</literal> independently. The ordering rule only has an effect when both tasks are scheduled for execution.</listitem>
            <listitem>When run with <literal>--continue</literal>, it is possible for <literal>B</literal> to execute in the event that <literal>A</literal> fails.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>As mentioned before, the “should run after” ordering rule will be ignored if it introduces an ordering cycle:</para>
        <sample id="shouldRunAfterWithCycle" dir="userguide/tasks/shouldRunAfterWithCycle" title="A 'should run after' task ordering is ignored if it introduces an ordering cycle">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:adding_a_description_to_a_task">
        <title>Adding a description to a task</title>
        <para>You can add a description to your task. This description is displayed when executing
            <userinput>gradle tasks</userinput>.
        </para>
        <sample id="describeTask" dir="userguide/tasks/defineAndConfigure" title="Adding a description to a task">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:replacing_tasks">
        <title>Replacing tasks</title>
        <para>Sometimes you want to replace a task. For example, if you want to exchange a task added by the Java plugin
            with a custom task of a different type. You can achieve this with:
        </para>
        <sample id="replaceTask" dir="userguide/tutorial/replaceTask" title="Overwriting a task">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q copy"/>
        </sample>
        <para>This will replace a task of type <literal>Copy</literal> with the task you've defined, because it
        uses the same name. When you define the new task, you have to set the <literal>overwrite</literal> property
        to true. Otherwise Gradle throws an exception, saying that a task with that name already exists.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:skipping_tasks">
        <title>Skipping tasks</title>
        <para>Gradle offers multiple ways to skip the execution of a task.</para>

        <section id="sec:using_a_predicate">
            <title>Using a predicate</title>
            <para>You can use the <literal>onlyIf()</literal> method to attach a predicate to a task. The task's
                actions are only executed if the predicate evaluates to true. You implement the predicate as a closure.
                The closure is passed the task as a parameter, and should return true if the task should execute
                and false if the task should be skipped. The predicate is evaluated just before the task is due
                to be executed.
                </para>
            <sample id="taskOnlyIf" dir="userguide/tutorial/taskOnlyIf" title="Skipping a task using a predicate">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
                <output args="hello -PskipHello"/>
            </sample>
        </section>

        <section id="sec:using_stopexecutionexception">
        <title>Using StopExecutionException</title>
        <para>If the logic for skipping a task can't be expressed with a predicate, you can use the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.StopExecutionException"/>. If this exception is thrown by an action,
            the further execution of this action as well as the execution of
            any following action of this task is skipped. The build continues with executing the next task.
        </para>
        <sample id="stopExecutionException" dir="userguide/tutorial/stopExecutionException" title="Skipping tasks with StopExecutionException">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q myTask"/>
        </sample>
        <para>This feature is helpful if you work with tasks provided by Gradle. It allows you to add
            <emphasis>conditional</emphasis> execution of the built-in actions of such a task.
            <footnote>
                <para>You might be wondering why there is neither an import for the
                    <literal>StopExecutionException</literal>
                    nor do we access it via its fully qualified name. The reason is, that Gradle adds a set of default imports
                    to your script (see <xref linkend='script-default-imports'/>).
                </para>
            </footnote>
        </para>
        </section>

        <section id="sec:enabling_and_disabling_tasks">
        <title>Enabling and disabling tasks</title>
        <para>Every task has an <literal>enabled</literal>
            flag which defaults to <literal>true</literal>. Setting it to <literal>false</literal> prevents the
            execution of any of the task's actions. A disabled task will be labelled SKIPPED.
        </para>
        <sample id="disableTask" dir="userguide/tutorial/disableTask" title="Enabling and disabling tasks">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="disableMe"/>
        </sample>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="sec:up_to_date_checks">
        <title>Up-to-date checks (AKA Incremental Build)</title>
        <para>An important part of any build tool is the ability to avoid doing work that has already
            been done. Consider the process of compilation. Once your source files have been compiled,
            there should be no need to recompile them unless something has changed that affects the
            output, such as the modification of a source file or the removal of an output file. And
            compilation can take a significant amount of time, so skipping the step when it’s not needed
            saves a lot of time.
        </para>
        <para>Gradle supports this behavior out of the box through a feature it calls incremental build.
            You have almost certainly already seen it in action: it’s active nearly every time the
            <literal>UP-TO-DATE</literal> text appears next to the name of a task when you run a build.
            Task outcomes are described in <xref linkend="sec:task_outcomes"/>.
        </para>
        <para>How does incremental build work? And what does it take to make use of it in your own
            tasks? Let’s take a look.
        </para>

        <section id="sec:task_inputs_outputs">
            <title>Task inputs and outputs</title>
            <para>In the most common case, a task takes some inputs and generates some outputs. If we
                use the compilation example from earlier, we can see that the source files are the
                inputs and, in the case of Java, the generated class files are the outputs. Other inputs
                might include things like whether debug information should be included.
            </para>

            <figure>
                <title>Example task inputs and outputs</title>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="img/taskInputsOutputs.png" width="160mm"/>
                </imageobject>
            </figure>

            <para>An important characteristic of an input is that it affects one or more outputs, as
                you can see from the previous figure. Different bytecode is generated depending on the
                content of the source files and the minimum version of the Java runtime you want to
                run the code on. That makes them task inputs. But whether the compilation runs in a
                forked process or not, determined by the <literal>fork</literal> property, has no
                impact on what bytecode gets generated. In Gradle terminology, <literal>fork</literal>
                is just an internal task property.
            </para>
            <para>As part of incremental build, Gradle tests whether any of the task inputs or outputs
                have changed since the last build. If they haven’t, Gradle can consider the task up to
                date and therefore skip executing its actions. Also note that incremental build won’t
                work unless a task has at least one task output, although tasks usually have at least
                one input as well.
            </para>
            <para>What this means for build authors is simple: you need to tell Gradle which task
                properties are inputs and which are outputs. If a task property affects the output, be
                sure to register it as an input, otherwise the task will be considered up to date when
                it’s not. Conversely, don’t register properties as inputs if they don’t affect the
                output, otherwise the task will potentially execute when it doesn’t need to. Also be
                careful of non-deterministic tasks that may generate different output for exactly the
                same inputs: these should not be configured for incremental build as the up-to-date
                checks won’t work.
            </para>
            <para>Let’s now look at how you can register task properties as inputs and outputs.</para>

            <section id="sec:task_input_output_annotations">
                <title>Custom task types</title>
                <para>If you’re implementing a custom task as a class, then it takes just two steps to
                    make it work with incremental build:
                </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>Create typed fields or properties (via getter methods) for each of your
                        task inputs and outputs</listitem>
                    <listitem>Add the appropriate annotation to each of those fields or getter methods
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>Gradle supports three main categories of inputs and outputs:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>Simple values</para>
                        <para>Things like strings and numbers. More generally, a simple value can have
                        any type that implements <literal>Serializable</literal>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Filesystem types</para>
                        <para>These consist of the standard <literal>File</literal> class but also
                        derivatives of Gradle’s <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileCollection"/>
                        type and anything else that can be passed to either the
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="file(java.lang.Object)"/>
                        method - for single file/directory properties - or the
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="files(java.lang.Object...)"/>
                        method.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Nested values</para>
                        <para>Custom types that don’t conform to the other two categories but have
                        their own properties that are inputs or outputs. In effect, the task inputs
                        or outputs are nested inside these custom types.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>As an example, imagine you have a task that processes templates of varying types,
                    such as FreeMarker, Velocity, Moustache, etc. It takes template source files and
                    combines them with some model data to generate populated versions of the template files.
                </para>
                <para>This task will have three inputs and one output:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Template source files</listitem>
                    <listitem>Model data</listitem>
                    <listitem>Template engine</listitem>
                    <listitem>Where the output files are written</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>When you’re writing a custom task class, it’s easy to register properties as
                    inputs or outputs via annotations. To demonstrate, here is a skeleton task
                    implementation with some suitable inputs and outputs, along with their annotations:
                </para>
                <sample id="customTaskClassWithInputOutputAnnotations"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                        title="Custom task class">
                    <sourcefile file="buildSrc/src/main/java/org/example/ProcessTemplates.java"
                                snippet="custom-task-class"/>
                    <sourcefile file="buildSrc/src/main/java/org/example/TemplateData.java"/>
                    <output args="processTemplates" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    <output args="processTemplates" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"
                            outputFile="customTaskClassWithInputOutputAnnotationsUpToDate.out"/>
                </sample>
                <para>There’s plenty to talk about in this example, so let’s work through each of the
                    input and output properties in turn:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><literal>templateEngine</literal></para>
                        <para>Represents which engine to use when processing the source templates, e.g.
                            FreeMarker, Velocity, etc. You could implement this as a string, but in this
                            case we have gone for a custom enum as it provides greater type information
                            and safety. Since enums implement <literal>Serializable</literal> automatically,
                            we can treat this as a simple value and use the <literal>@Input</literal>
                            annotation, just as we would with a <literal>String</literal> property.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>sourceFiles</literal></para>
                        <para>The source templates that the task will be processing. Single files and
                            collections of files need their own special annotations. In this case, we’re
                            dealing with a collection of input files and so we use the
                            <literal>@InputFiles</literal> annotation. You’ll see more file-oriented
                            annotations in a table later.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>templateData</literal></para>
                        <para>For this example, we’re using a custom class to represent the model data.
                            However, it does not implement <literal>Serializable</literal>, so we can’t
                            use the <literal>@Input</literal> annotation. That’s not a problem as the
                            properties within <literal>TemplateData</literal> - a string and a hash map
                            with serializable type parameters - are serializable and can be annotated with
                            <literal>@Input</literal>. We use <literal>@Nested</literal> on
                            <literal>templateData</literal> to let Gradle know that this is a value with
                            nested input properties.
                       </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>outputDir</literal></para>
                        <para>The directory where the generated files go. As with input files, there are
                            several annotations for output files and directories. A property representing
                            a single directory requires <literal>@OutputDirectory</literal>. You’ll learn
                            about the others soon.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>These annotated properties mean that Gradle will skip the task if none of the source
                    files, template engine, model data or generated files have changed since the previous
                    time Gradle executed the task. This will often save a significant amount of time. You
                    can learn how Gradle detects <link linkend="sec:how_does_it_work">changes later</link>.
                </para>

                <para>This example is particularly interesting because it works with collections of source
                    files. What happens if only one source file changes? Does the task process all the
                    source files again or just the modified one? That depends on the task implementation.
                    If the latter, then the task itself is incremental, but that’s a different feature to
                    the one we’re discussing here. Gradle does help task implementers with this via its
                    <link linkend="incremental_tasks">incremental task inputs</link> feature.
                </para>

                <para>Now that you have seen some of the input and output annotations in practice, let’s
                    take a look at all the annotations available to you and when you should use them. The
                    table below lists the available annotations and the corresponding property type you
                    can use with each one.
                </para>

                <table>
                    <title>Incremental build property type annotations</title>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Annotation</th>
                            <th>Expected property type</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Input"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Any serializable type</td>
                        <td>A simple input value</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.InputFile"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>File</literal>*</td>
                        <td>A single input file (not directory)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.InputDirectory"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>File</literal>*</td>
                        <td>A single input directory (not file)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.InputFiles"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>*</td>
                        <td>An iterable of input files and directories</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Classpath"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>*</td>
                        <td>An iterable of input files and directories that represent a Java classpath.
                            This allows the task to ignore irrelevant changes to the property, such as
                            different names for the same files. It is similar to annotating the property
                            <literal>@PathSensitive(RELATIVE)</literal> but it will ignore the names of
                            JAR files directly added to the classpath, and it will consider changes in the
                            order of the files as a change in the classpath.

                            Gradle will inspect the contents of jar files on the classpath and ignore changes
                            that do not affect the semantics of the classpath (such as file dates and entry order).
                            <note>
                                <para>To stay compatible with Gradle versions before 3.2, classpath properties
                                    should also be annotated with <literal>@InputFiles</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </note>
                        </td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.CompileClasspath"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>*</td>
                        <td>An iterable of input files and directories that represent a Java compile classpath.
                            This allows the task to ignore irrelevant changes that do not affect the API of the classes in classpath.
                            The following kinds of changes to the classpath will be ignored:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                 <listitem>Changes to the path of jar or top level directories.</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to timestamps and the order of entries in Jars.</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to resources and Jar manifests, including adding or removing resources.</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to private class elements, such as private fields, methods and inner classes.</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to code, such as method bodies, static initializers and field initializers (except for constants).</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to debug information, for example when a change to a comment affects the line numbers in class debug information.</listitem>
                                 <listitem>Changes to directories, including directory entries in Jars.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <note>
                                <para>To stay compatible with Gradle versions before 3.2, classpath properties
                                    should also be annotated with <literal>@InputFiles</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </note>
                        </td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.OutputFile"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>File</literal>*</td>
                        <td>A single output file (not directory)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.OutputDirectory"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>File</literal>*</td>
                        <td>A single output directory (not file)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.OutputFiles"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>Map&lt;String, File&gt;</literal>** or <literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>*</td>
                        <td>An iterable of output files (no directories)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.OutputDirectories"/></literal></td>
                        <td><literal>Map&lt;String, File&gt;</literal>** or <literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>*</td>
                        <td>An iterable of output directories (no files)</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Nested"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Any custom type</td>
                        <td>A custom type that may not implement <literal>Serializable</literal> but does
                            have at least one field or property marked with one of the annotations in this
                            table. It could even be another <literal>@Nested</literal>.</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Console"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Any type</td>
                        <td>Indicates that the property is neither an input nor an output. It simply
                            affects the console output of the task in some way, such as increasing or
                            decreasing the verbosity of the task.</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Internal"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Any type</td>
                        <td>Indicates that the property is used internally but is neither an input nor
                            an output.</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tfoot>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="3"><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis> In fact, <literal>File</literal>
                                can be any type accepted by
                                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="file(java.lang.Object)"/>
                                and <literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal> can be any type accepted by
                                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="files(java.lang.Object...)"/>.
                                This includes instances of <literal>Callable</literal>, such as closures,
                                allowing for lazy evaluation of the property values. Be aware that the types
                                <literal>FileCollection</literal> and <literal>FileTree</literal> are
                                <literal>Iterable&lt;File&gt;</literal>s.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="3"><emphasis role="bold">**</emphasis> Similar to the above,
                                <literal>File</literal> can be any type accepted by
                                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="file(java.lang.Object)"/>.
                                The <literal>Map</literal> itself can be wrapped in <literal>Callable</literal>s,
                                such as closures.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tfoot>
                </table>

                <table>
                    <title>Additional annotations used to further qualifying property type annotations</title>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Annotation</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <anchor id="skip-when-empty"/>
                            <literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.SkipWhenEmpty"/></literal>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                Used with <literal>@InputFiles</literal> or <literal>@InputDirectory</literal>
                                to tell Gradle to skip the task if the corresponding files or
                                directory are empty, along with all other input files declared with this annotation.

                                Tasks that have been skipped due to all of their input files that were declared with this
                                annotation being empty will result in a distinct “no source” outcome.
                                For example, <literal>NO-SOURCE</literal> will be emitted in the console output.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Optional"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Used with any of the property type annotations listed in the
                            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Optional"/> API documentation.
                            This annotation disables validation checks on the corresponding property.
                            See <link linkend="sec:task_input_output_validation">the section on validation</link>
                            for more details.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><literal>@<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.PathSensitive"/></literal></td>
                        <td>Used with any input file property to tell Gradle to only consider the given
                            part of the file paths as important. For example, if a property is annotated
                            with <literal>@PathSensitive(PathSensitivity.NAME_ONLY)</literal>, then
                            moving the files around without changing their contents will not make the
                            task out-of-date.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>

                <para>Annotations are inherited from all parent types including implemented interfaces.
                    Property type annotations override any other property type annotation declared in a
                    parent type. This way an <literal>@InputFile</literal> property can be turned into
                    an <literal>@InputDirectory</literal> property in a child task type.
                </para>

                <para>Annotations on a property declared in a type override similar annotations declared
                    by the superclass and in any implemented interfaces. Superclass annotations take
                    precedence over annotations declared in implemented interfaces.
                </para>

                <para>The <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Console"/> and
                    <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Internal"/> annotations in the table are special
                    cases as they don’t declare either task inputs or task outputs. So why use them? It's
                    so that you can take advantage of the <link linkend="javaGradle_plugin">Java Gradle
                    Plugin Development plugin</link> to help you develop and publish your own plugins.
                    This plugin checks whether any properties of your custom task classes lack an
                    incremental build annotation. This protects you from forgetting to add an appropriate
                    annotation during development.
                </para>

                <para>Custom task classes are an easy way to bring your own build logic into the arena
                    of incremental build, but you don’t always have that option. That's why Gradle also
                    provides an alternative API that can be used with any tasks, which we look at next.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section id="sec:task_input_output_runtime_api">
                <title>Runtime API</title>
                <para>When you don’t have access to the source for a custom task class, there is no way
                    to add any of the annotations we covered in the previous section. Fortunately, Gradle
                    provides a runtime API for scenarios just like that. It can also be used for ad-hoc
                    tasks, as you'll see next.
                </para>

                <section id="sec:runtime_api_for_adhoc">
                    <title>Using it for ad-hoc tasks</title>
                    <para>This runtime API is provided through a couple of aptly named properties that
                        are available on every Gradle task:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="getInputs()"/> of type <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskInputs"/>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="getOutputs()"/> of type <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskOutputs"/>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>These objects have methods that allow you to specify files, directories and
                        values which constitute the task’s inputs and outputs. In fact, the runtime API
                        has almost feature parity with the annotations. All it lacks is validation of
                        whether declared files are actually files and declared directories are directories.
                        Nor will it create output directories if they don't exist. But that's it.
                    </para>
                    <para>Let’s take the template processing example from before and see how it would
                        look as an ad-hoc task that uses the runtime API:</para>
                    <sample id="incrementalAdHocTask"
                            dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                            title="Ad-hoc task">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="ad-hoc-task"/>
                        <output args="processTemplatesAdHoc" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    </sample>
                    <para>As before, there’s much to talk about. To begin with, you should really write
                        a custom task class for this as it’s a non-trivial implementation that has
                        several configuration options. In this case, there are no task properties to
                        store the root source folder, the location of the output directory or any of
                        the other settings. That’s deliberate to highlight the fact that the runtime
                        API doesn’t require the task to have any state. In terms of incremental build,
                        the above ad-hoc task will behave the same as the custom task class.
                    </para>
                    <para>All the input and output definitions are done through the methods on
                        <literal>inputs</literal> and <literal>outputs</literal>, such as
                        <literal>property()</literal>, <literal>files()</literal>, and
                        <literal>dir()</literal>. Gradle performs up-to-date checks on the argument
                        values to determine whether the task needs to run again or not. Each method
                        corresponds to one of the incremental build annotations, for example
                        <literal>inputs.property()</literal> maps to <literal>@Input</literal> and
                        <literal>outputs.dir()</literal> maps to <literal>@OutputDirectory</literal>.
                        The only difference is that the <literal>file()</literal>, <literal>files()</literal>,
                        <literal>dir()</literal> and <literal>dirs()</literal> methods don’t validate
                        the type of file object at the given path (file or directory), unlike the annotations.
                    </para>
                    <para>One notable difference between the runtime API and the annotations is the
                        lack of a method that corresponds directly to <literal>@Nested</literal>.
                        That’s why the example uses two <literal>property()</literal> declarations
                        for the template data, one for each <literal>TemplateData</literal> property.
                        You should utilize the same technique when using the runtime API with nested
                        values.
                    </para>
                </section>

                <section id="sec:runtime_api_for_custom_tasks">
                    <title>Using it for custom task types</title>
                    <para>Another type of example involves adding input and output definitions to
                        instances of a custom task class that lacks the requisite annotations. For
                        example, imagine that the <literal>ProcessTemplates</literal> task is provided
                        by a plugin and that it’s missing the incremental build annotations. In order
                        to make up for that deficiency, you can use the runtime API:
                    </para>
                    <sample id="runtimeIncrementalApi"
                            dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                            title="Using runtime API with custom task type">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="custom-class-runtime-api"/>
                        <output args="processTemplatesRuntime" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                        <output args="processTemplatesRuntime" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"
                                outputFile="runtimeIncrementalApiUpToDate.out"/>
                    </sample>
                    <para>As you can see, we can both configure the tasks properties and use those
                        properties as arguments to the incremental build runtime API. Using the runtime
                        API like this is a little like using <literal>doLast()</literal> and
                        <literal>doFirst()</literal> to attach extra actions to a task, except in this
                        case we’re attaching information about inputs and outputs. Note that if the
                        task type is already using the incremental build annotations, the runtime API
                        will add inputs and outputs rather than replace them.
                    </para>
                </section>

                <section id="sec:runtime_api_configuration">
                    <title>Fine-grained configuration</title>
                    <para>The runtime API methods only allow you to declare your inputs and outputs in
                        themselves. However, the file-oriented ones return a builder - of type
                        <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskInputFilePropertyBuilder"/> - that let’s
                        you provide additional information about those inputs and outputs.
                    </para>
                    <para>You can learn about all the options provided by the builder in its API
                        documentation, but we’ll show you a simple example here to give you an idea of
                        what you can do.
                    </para>
                    <para>Let’s say we don’t want to run the <literal>processTemplates</literal> task
                        if there are no source files, regardless of whether it’s a clean build or not.
                        After all, if there are no source files, there’s nothing for the task to do. The
                        builder allows us to configure this like so:
                    </para>
                    <sample id="runtimeIncrementalApiConfiguration"
                            dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                            title="Using skipWhenEmpty() via the runtime API">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="runtime-api-conf"/>
                        <output args="clean processTemplatesRuntimeConf"
                                ignoreExtraLines="true"
                                ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    </sample>
                    <para>The <literal>TaskInputs.files()</literal> method returns a builder that has
                        a <literal>skipWhenEmpty()</literal> method.
                        Invoking this method is equivalent to annotating to the property with <link linkend="skip-when-empty"><literal>@SkipWhenEmpty</literal></link>.
                    </para>
                    <para>Prior to Gradle 3.0, you had to use the <literal>TaskInputs.source()</literal>
                        and <literal>TaskInputs.sourceDir()</literal> methods to get the same behavior
                        as with <literal>skipWhenEmpty()</literal>. These methods are now deprecated and
                        should not be used with Gradle 3.0 and above.
                    </para>
                    <para>Now that you have seen both the annotations and the runtime API, you may be
                        wondering which API you should be using. Our recommendation is to use the
                        annotations wherever possible, and it’s sometimes worth creating a custom task
                        class just so that you can make use of them. The runtime API is more for situations
                        in which you can’t use the annotations.
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section id="sec:task_input_output_side_effects">
                <title>Important beneficial side effects</title>
                <para>Once you declare a task’s formal inputs and outputs, Gradle can then infer things
                    about those properties. For example, if an input of one task is set to the output of
                    another, that means the first task depends on the second, right? Gradle knows this
                    and can act upon it.
                </para>
                <para>We’ll look at this feature next and also some other features that come from Gradle
                    knowing things about inputs and outputs.
                </para>

                <section id="sec:inferred_task_dependencies">
                    <title>Inferred task dependencies</title>
                    <para>Consider an archive task that packages the output of the
                        <literal>processTemplates</literal> task. A build author will see that the archive
                        task obviously requires <literal>processTemplates</literal> to run first and so
                        may add an explicit <literal>dependsOn</literal>. However, if you define the
                        archive task like so:
                    </para>
                    <sample id="inferredTaskDep"
                            dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                            title="Inferred task dependency via task outputs">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="inferred-task-dep-via-outputs"/>
                        <output args="clean packageFiles" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    </sample>
                    <para>Gradle will automatically make <literal>packageFiles</literal> depend on
                        <literal>processTemplates</literal>. It can do this because it’s aware that one
                        of the inputs of packageFiles requires the output of the processTemplates task.
                        We call this an inferred task dependency.
                    </para>
                    <para>The above example can also be written as</para>
                    <sample id="inferredTaskDep2"
                            dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/customTaskClass"
                            title="Inferred task dependency via a task argument">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="inferred-task-dep-via-task"/>
                        <output args="clean packageFiles2" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    </sample>
                    <para>This is because the <literal>from()</literal> method can accept a task object
                        as an argument. Behind the scenes, <literal>from()</literal> uses the
                        <literal>project.files()</literal> method to wrap the argument, which in turn
                        exposes the task’s formal outputs as a file collection. In other words, it’s a
                        special case!
                    </para>
                </section>

                <section id="sec:task_input_output_validation">
                    <title>Input and output validation</title>
                    <para>The incremental build annotations provide enough information for Gradle to
                        perform some basic validation on the annotated properties. In particular, it does
                        the following for each property before the task executes:
                    </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><literal>@InputFile</literal> - verifies that the property has a value
                            and that the path corresponds to a file (not a directory) that exists.
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem><literal>@InputDirectory</literal> - same as for <literal>@InputFile</literal>,
                            except the path must correspond to a directory.
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem><literal>@OutputDirectory</literal> - verifies that the path doesn’t
                            match a file and also creates the directory if it doesn’t already exist.
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>Such validation improves the robustness of the build, allowing you to identify
                        issues related to inputs and outputs quickly.
                    </para>
                    <para>You will occasionally want to disable some of this validation, specifically
                        when an input file may validly not exist. That’s why Gradle provides the
                        <literal>@Optional</literal> annotation: you use it to tell Gradle that a
                        particular input is optional and therefore the build should not fail if the
                        corresponding file or directory doesn’t exist.
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section id="sec:task_input_output_continuous_build">
                    <title>Continuous build</title>
                    <para>One last benefit of defining task inputs and outputs is continuous build. Since
                        Gradle knows what files a task depends on, it can automatically run a task again
                        if any of its inputs change. By activating continuous build when you run Gradle -
                        through the <literal>--continuous</literal> or <literal>-t</literal> options - you
                        will put Gradle into a state in which it continually checks for changes and executes
                        the requested tasks when it encounters such changes.
                    </para>
                    <para>You can find out more about this feature in <xref linkend="continuous_build"/>.
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section id="sec:advanced_inc_build">
            <title>Advanced techniques</title>
            <para>Everything you’ve seen so far in this section will cover most of the use cases you’ll
                encounter, but there are some scenarios that need special treatment. We’ll present a few
                of those next with the appropriate solutions.
            </para>

            <section id="sec:add_cached_input_output_methods">
                <title>Adding your own cached input/output methods</title>
                <para>Have you ever wondered how the <literal>from()</literal> method of the
                    <literal>Copy</literal> task works? It’s not annotated with <literal>@InputFiles</literal>
                    and yet any files passed to it are treated as formal inputs of the task. What’s
                    happening?
                </para>
                <para>The implementation is quite simple and you can use the same technique for your own
                    tasks to improve their APIs. Write your methods so that they add files directly to
                    the appropriate annotated property. As an example, here’s how to add a
                    <literal>sources()</literal> method to the custom <literal>ProcessTemplates</literal>
                    class we introduced earlier:
                </para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildCustomMethods"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Declaring a method to add task inputs">
                    <sourcefile file="buildSrc/src/main/java/org/example/ProcessTemplates.java"
                                snippet="custom-task-class"/>
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="custom-task-class"/>
                    <output args="processTemplates" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>In other words, as long as you add values and files to formal task inputs and outputs
                    during the configuration phase, they will be treated as such regardless from where in
                    the build you add them.
                </para>
                <para>If we want to support tasks as arguments as well and treat their outputs as the
                    inputs, we can use the <literal>project.files()</literal> method like so:
                </para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildCustomMethodsWithTaskArg"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Declaring a method to add a task as an input">
                    <sourcefile file="buildSrc/src/main/java/org/example/ProcessTemplates.java"
                                snippet="task-arg-method"/>
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="task-arg-method"/>
                    <output args="processTemplates2" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>This technique can make your custom task easier to use and result in cleaner build
                    files. As an added benefit, our use of <literal>getProject().files()</literal> means
                    that our custom method can set up an inferred task dependency.</para>
                <para>One last thing to note: if you are developing a task that takes collections of source
                    files as inputs, like this example, consider using the built-in
                    <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.SourceTask"/>. It will save you having to
                    implement some of the plumbing that we put into <literal>ProcessTemplates</literal>.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section id="sec:link_output_dir_to_input_files">
                <title>Linking an <literal>@OutputDirectory</literal> to an <literal>@InputFiles</literal></title>
                <para>When you want to link the output of one task to the input of another, the types
                    often match and a simple property assignment will provide that link. For example, a
                    <literal>File</literal> output property can be assigned to a <literal>File</literal>
                    input.
                </para>
                <para>Unfortunately, this approach breaks down when you want the files in a task’s
                    <literal>@OutputDirectory</literal> (of type <literal>File</literal>) to become the
                    source for another task’s <literal>@InputFiles</literal> property (of type
                    <literal>FileCollection</literal>). Since the two have different types, property
                    assignment won’t work.
                </para>
                <para>As an example, imagine you want to use the output of a Java compilation task - via
                    the <literal>destinationDir</literal> property - as the input of a custom task that
                    instruments a set of files containing Java bytecode. This custom task, which we’ll
                    call <literal>Instrument</literal>, has a <literal>classFiles</literal> property
                    annotated with <literal>@InputFiles</literal>. You might initially try to configure
                    the task like so:
                </para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildBadInputFilesConfig"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Failed attempt at setting up an inferred task dependency">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="failed-inferred-task-dep"/>
                    <output args="clean badInstrumentClasses" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>There’s nothing obviously wrong with this code, but you can see from the console
                    output that the compilation task is missing. In this case you would need to add an
                    explicit task dependency between <literal>instrumentClasses</literal> and
                    <literal>compileJava</literal> via <literal>dependsOn</literal>. The use of
                    <literal>fileTree()</literal> means that Gradle can’t infer the task dependency itself.
                </para>
                <para>One solution is to use the <literal>TaskOutputs.files</literal> property, as
                    demonstrated by the following example:</para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildInputFilesConfig"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Setting up an inferred task dependency between output dir and input files">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="inferred-task-dep"/>
                    <output args="clean instrumentClasses" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>Alternatively, you can get Gradle to access the appropriate property itself by using the
                    <literal>project.files()</literal> method in place of <literal>project.fileTree()</literal>:
                </para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildInputFilesConfigUsingTask"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Setting up an inferred task dependency with files()">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="inferred-task-dep-with-files"/>
                    <output args="clean instrumentClasses2" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>Remember that <literal>files()</literal> can take tasks as arguments, whereas
                    <literal>fileTree()</literal> cannot.
                </para>
                <para>The downside of this approach is that all file outputs of the source task become the
                    input files of the target - <literal>instrumentClasses</literal> in this case. That’s fine
                    as long as the source task only has a single file-based output, like the
                    <literal>JavaCompile</literal> task. But if you have to link just one output property
                    among several, then you need to explicitly tell Gradle which task generates the input
                    files using the <literal>builtBy</literal> method:
                </para>
                <sample id="inferredTaskDependencyWithBuiltBy"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Setting up an inferred task dependency with builtBy()">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="inferred-task-dep-with-builtby"/>
                    <output args="clean instrumentClassesBuiltBy" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                </sample>
                <para>You can of course just add an explicit task dependency via <literal>dependsOn</literal>,
                    but the above approach provides more semantic meaning, explaining why
                    <literal>compileJava</literal> has to run beforehand.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section id="sec:custom_up_to_date_logic">
                <title>Providing custom up-to-date logic</title>
                <para>Gradle automatically handles up-to-date checks for output files and directories, but what
                    if the task output is something else entirely? Perhaps it’s an update to a web service or a
                    database table. Gradle has no way of knowing how to check whether the task is up to date in
                    such cases.
                </para>
                <para>That’s where the <literal>upToDateWhen()</literal> method on <literal>TaskOutputs</literal>
                    comes in. This takes a predicate function that is used to determine whether a task is up to
                    date or not. One use case is to disable up-to-date checks completely for a task, like so:
                </para>
                <sample id="incrementalBuildUpToDateWhen"
                        dir="userguide/tasks/incrementalBuild/incrementalBuildAdvanced"
                        title="Ignoring up-to-date checks">
                    <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="up-to-date-when"/>
                    <test args="clean"/>
                    <output args="clean alwaysInstrumentClasses" ignoreExtraLines="true" ignoreLineOrder="true"/>
                    <output args="alwaysInstrumentClasses" ignoreExtraLines="true"
                            ignoreLineOrder="true" outputFile="incrementalBuildUpToDateWhenAgain.out"/>
                </sample>
                <para>The <literal>{ false }</literal> closure ensures that <literal>copyResources</literal>
                    will always perform the copy, irrespective of whether there is no change in the inputs or
                    outputs.
                </para>
                <para>You can of course put more complex logic into the closure. You could check whether a
                    particular record in a database table exists or has changed for example. Just be aware
                    that up-to-date checks should _save_ you time. Don’t add checks that cost as much or
                    more time than the standard execution of the task. In fact, if a task ends up running
                    frequently anyway, because it’s rarely up to date, then it may not be worth having an
                    up-to-date check at all. Remember that your checks will always run if the task is in the
                    execution task graph.
                </para>
                <para>One common mistake is to use <literal>upToDateWhen()</literal> instead of
                    <literal>Task.onlyIf()</literal>. If you want to skip a task on the basis of some condition
                    unrelated to the task inputs and outputs, then you should use <literal>onlyIf()</literal>.
                    For example, in cases where you want to skip a task when a particular property is set or
                    not set.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="sec:how_does_it_work">
            <title>How does it work?</title>
            <para>
                Before a task is executed for the first time, Gradle takes a snapshot of the inputs. This snapshot contains
                the paths of input files and a hash of the contents of each file. Gradle then executes the task. If the
                task completes successfully, Gradle takes a snapshot of the outputs. This snapshot contains the set of
                output files and a hash of the contents of each file. Gradle persists both snapshots for the next time the task
                is executed.
            </para>
            <para>
                Each time after that, before the task is executed, Gradle takes a new snapshot of the inputs and outputs.
                If the new snapshots are the same as the previous snapshots, Gradle assumes that the outputs are up to
                date and skips the task. If they are not the same, Gradle executes the task. Gradle persists both snapshots
                for the next time the task is executed.
            </para>
            <para>
                Gradle also considers the <emphasis>code</emphasis> of the task as part of the inputs to the task. When a task,
                its actions, or its dependencies change between executions, Gradle considers the task as out-of-date.
            </para>
            <para>
                Gradle understands if a file property (e.g. one holding a Java classpath) is order-sensitive. When comparing
                the snapshot of such a property, even a change in the order of the files will result in the task becoming
                out-of-date.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that if a task has an output directory specified, any files added to that directory since the last time it was executed
                are ignored and will NOT cause the task to be out of date. This is so unrelated tasks may share an output directory without interfering with each other.
                If this is not the behaviour you want for some reason, consider using <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.TaskOutputs" method="upToDateWhen(groovy.lang.Closure)" />
            </para>
            <para>
                The inputs for the task are also used to calculate the <link linkend="build_cache">build cache</link> key used to load task outputs when enabled.
                For more details see <xref linkend="sec:task_output_caching_faster"/>.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:task_rules">
        <title>Task rules</title>
        <para>Sometimes you want to have a task whose behavior depends on a large or infinite number value range
            of parameters. A very nice and expressive way to provide such tasks are task rules:
        </para>
        <sample id="taskRule" dir="userguide/tasks/addRules" title="Task rule">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="task-rule"/>
            <output args="-q pingServer1"/>
        </sample>
        <para>The String parameter is used as a description for the rule, which is shown with <userinput>gradle tasks</userinput>.
        </para>
        <para>Rules are not only used when calling tasks from the command line. You can also create dependsOn relations
            on rule based tasks:
        </para>
        <sample id="taskRuleDependsOn" dir="userguide/tasks/addRules" title="Dependency on rule based tasks">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q groupPing"/>
        </sample>
        <para>If you run “<literal>gradle -q tasks</literal>” you won't find a task named
        “<literal>pingServer1</literal>” or “<literal>pingServer2</literal>”, but this script is executing logic
        based on the request to run those tasks.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:finalizer_tasks">
        <title>Finalizer tasks</title>
        <note>
            <para>
                Finalizers tasks are an <firstterm>incubating</firstterm> feature (see <xref linkend="sec:incubating_state"/>).
            </para>
        </note>
        <para>Finalizer tasks are automatically added to the task graph when the finalized task is scheduled to run.</para>
        <sample id="taskFinalizers" dir="userguide/tasks/finalizers" title="Adding a task finalizer">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Finalizer tasks will be executed even if the finalized task fails.</para>
        <sample id="taskFinalizersWithFailure" dir="userguide/tasks/finalizersWithFailure" title="Task finalizer for a failing task">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
            <output args="-q taskX"/>
        </sample>
        <para>On the other hand, finalizer tasks are not executed if the finalized task didn't do any work, for example if it
        is considered up to date or if a dependent task fails.</para>
        <para>Finalizer tasks are useful in situations where the build creates a resource that has to be cleaned up regardless
            of the build failing or succeeding. An example of such a resource is a web container that is started before an integration test task
            and which should be always shut down, even if some of the tests fail.</para>
        <para>To specify a finalizer task you use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="finalizedBy"/> method.
            This method accepts a task instance, a task name, or any other input accepted by <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Task" method="dependsOn"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:lifecycle_tasks">
        <title>Lifecycle tasks</title>
        <para>
            Lifecycle tasks are tasks that do not do work themselves. They typically do not have any task actions.  Lifecycle tasks can represent several concepts:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>a work-flow step (e.g., run all checks with <literal>check</literal>)</listitem>
            <listitem>a buildable thing (e.g., create a debug 32-bit executable for native components with <literal>debug32MainExecutable</literal>)</listitem>
            <listitem>a convenience task to execute many of the same logical tasks (e.g., run all compilation tasks with <literal>compileAll</literal>)</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            Many Gradle plug-ins define their own lifecycle tasks to make it convenient to do specific things.
            When developing your own plugins, you should consider using your own lifecycle tasks or hooking into some of the tasks already provided by Gradle.
            See the Java plugin <xref linkend="sec:java_tasks"/> for an example.
        </para>
        <para>
            Unless a lifecycle task has actions, its outcome is determined by its dependencies.
            If any of the task's dependencies are executed, the lifecycle task will be considered executed.
            If all of the task's dependencies are up-to-date, skipped or from cache, the lifecycle task will be considered up-to-date.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:the_idea_behind_gradle_tasks">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>If you are coming from Ant, an enhanced Gradle task like <emphasis>Copy</emphasis> seems like a cross
            between an Ant target and an Ant task. Although Ant's tasks and targets are really different entities,
            Gradle combines these notions into a single entity. Simple Gradle tasks are like Ant's targets, but enhanced
            Gradle tasks also include aspects of Ant tasks. All of Gradle's tasks share a common API and you can create
            dependencies between them. These tasks are much easier to configure than an Ant task.
            They make full use of the type system, and are more expressive and easier to maintain.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
