<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='troubleshooting'>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <note>
        <para>
            This chapter is currently a work in progress.
        </para>
    </note>
    <para>
        When using Gradle (or any software package), you can run into problems. You may not understand
        how to use a particular feature, or you may encounter a defect. Or, you may have a general question
        about Gradle.
    </para>
    <para>
        This chapter gives some advice for troubleshooting problems and explains how to get help with your problems.
    </para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Working through problems</title>
        <para>
            If you are encountering problems, one of the first things to try is using the very latest release of Gradle. New versions of Gradle are
            released frequently with bug fixes and new features. The problem you are having may have been fixed in a new release.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you are using the Gradle Daemon, try temporarily disabling the daemon (you can pass the command line switch <literal>--no-daemon</literal>).
            More information about troubleshooting daemon is located in <xref linkend="gradle_daemon"/>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Getting help</title>
        <para>
            The place to go for help with Gradle is <ulink url="http://forums.gradle.org">http://forums.gradle.org</ulink>.
            The Gradle Forums is the place where you can report problems and ask questions to the Gradle 
            developers and other community members.
        </para>
        <para>
            If something's not working for you, posting a question or problem report to the forums is the fastest way 
            to get help. It's also the place to post improvement suggestions or new ideas. The development team 
            frequently posts news items and announces releases via the forum, making it a great way to stay up to 
            date with the latest Gradle developments.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>