<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id='dependency_management' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Dependency Management</title>
    <section id='sec:Introduction'>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>This chapter gives an overview of issues related with dependency management and presents how Gradle can be used to overcome them.
        </para>
        <para>Gradle offers a very good support for dependency management. If you are familiar with Maven or Ivy approach you will be delighted to learn that:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>All the concepts that you already know and like are still there and are fully supported by Gradle. The current dependency management solutions all require to work with XML descriptor files and are usually
        based on remote repositories for downloading the dependencies. Gradle fully supports this approach.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Gradle works <emphasis>perfectly</emphasis> with your existent dependency management
                    infrastructure, be it Maven or Ivy. All the repositories you have set up with your custom POM or
                    ivy files can be used as they are. No changes necessary.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Additionally, Gradle offers a simpler approach, which might be better suited for some projects.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id='sec:dependency_management_overview'>
        <title>Dependency management overview</title>
        <para>We think dependency management is very important for almost any project. Yet the kind of dependency
            management you need depends on the complexity and the environment of your project. Is your project a
            distribution or a library? Is it part of an enterprise environment, where it is integrated into other
            projects builds or not? But all types of projects share the following requirements:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The version of the jar must be easy to recognize. Sometimes the version is in the Manifest file of
                    the jar, often not. And even if, it is rather painful to always look into the Manifest file to learn
                    about the version. Therefore we think that you should only use jars which have their version as part
                    of their file name.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>It hopes to be clear what are the first level dependencies and what are the transitive ones. There
                    are different ways to achieve this. We will look at this later.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Conflicting versions of the same jar should be detected and either resolved or cause an exception.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section id='sub:versioning_the_jar_name'>
            <title>Versioning the jar name</title>
            <para>Why do we think this is necessary? Without a dependency management as described above, your are likely
                to burn your fingers sooner or later. If it is unclear which version of a jar your are using, this can
                introduce subtle bugs which are very hard to find. For example there might be a project which uses
                Hibernate 3.0.4. There are some problems with Hibernate so a developer installs version 3.0.5 of
                Hibernate on her machine. This did not solve the problem but she forgot to roll back Hibernate to 3.0.4.
                Weeks later there is an exception on the integration machine which can't be reproduced on the developer
                machine. Without a version in the jar name this problem might take a long time to debug. Version in the
                jar names increases the expressiveness of your project and makes it easier to maintain.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:transitive_dependency_management'>
            <title>Transitive dependency management</title>
            <para>Why is transitive dependency management so important? If you don't know which dependencies are first
                level dependencies and which ones are transitive you will soon lose control over your build. Even
                Gradle has already 20+ jars. An enterprise project using Spring, Hibernate, etc. easily ends up with
                100+ jars. There is no way to memorize where all these jars come from. If you want to get rid of a first
                level dependency you can't be sure which other jars you should remove. Because a dependency of a
                first level dependency might also be a first level dependency itself. Or it might be a transitive
                dependency of another of your first level dependencies. Many first level dependencies are runtime
                dependencies and the transitive dependencies are of course all runtime dependencies. So the compiler
                won't help you much here. The end of the story is, as we have seen very often, no one dares to remove
                any jar any longer. The project classpath is a complete mess and if a classpath problem arises, hell on
                earth invites you for a ride. In one of my former projects, I found some ldap related jar in the
                classpath, whose sheer presence, as I found out after much research, accelerated LDAP access. So
                removing this jar would not have led to any errors at compile or runtime.
            </para>
            <para>Gradle offers you different ways to express what are first level and what are transitive dependencies.
                Gradle allows you for example to store your jars in CVS or SVN without XML descriptor files and still
                use transitive dependency management. Gradle also validates your dependency hierarchy against the
                reality of your code by using only the first level dependencies for compiling.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:version_conflicts'>
            <title>Version conflicts</title>
            <para>In your dependency description you tell Gradle which version of a dependency is needed by another
                dependency. This frequently leads to conflicts. Different dependencies rely on different versions of
                another dependency. The JVM unfortunately does not offer yet any easy way, to have different versions of
                the same jar in the classpath (see <xref linkend='sub:dependency_management_and_java'/>). What Gradle
                offers you is a resolution strategy, by default the newest version is used. To deal with problems due to
                version conflicts, reports with dependency graphs are also very helpful. Such reports are another
                feature of dependency management.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:dependency_management_and_java'>
            <title>Dependency management and Java</title>
            <para>Traditionally, Java has offered no support at all for dealing with libraries and versions. There are
                no standard ways to say that
                <literal>foo-1.0.jar</literal>
                depends on a <literal>bar-2.0.jar</literal>. This has led to proprietary solutions. The most popular ones
                are Maven and Ivy. Maven is a complete build system whereas Ivy focuses solely on dependency management.
            </para>
            <para>Both approaches rely on descriptor XML files, which contains information about the dependencies of a
                particular jar. Both also use repositories where the actual jars are placed together with their
                descriptor files. And both offer resolution for conflicting jar versions in one form or the other. Yet
                we think the differences of both approaches are significant
                in terms of flexibility and maintainability. Beside this, Ivy fully supports the Maven dependency
                handling. So with Ivy you have access to both worlds. We like Ivy very much. Gradle uses it under the
                hood for its dependency management. Ivy is most often used via Ant and XML descriptors. But it also has
                an API. We integrate deeply with Ivy via its API. This enables us to build new concepts on top
                of Ivy which Ivy does not offer itself.
            </para>
            <para>Right now there is a lot of movement in the field of dependency handling. There is OSGi and there is
                JSR-294.
                <footnote>
                    <para>JSR 294: Improved Modularity Support in the JavaTM Programming Language, <ulink url='http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=294'/>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
                OSGi is available already, JSR-294 is supposed to be shipped with Java 7. These technologies
                deal, amongst many other things, also with a painful problem which is neither solved by Maven nor by Ivy. This is enabling different
                versions of the same jar to be used at runtime.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id='sec:how_to_declare_your_dependencies'>
        <title>How to declare your dependencies</title>
        <para>People who know Ivy have come across most of the concepts we are going to introduce now. But Gradle does not
            use any XML for declaring the dependencies (e.g. no <literal>ivy.xml</literal> file). It has its own
            notation which is part of the Gradle build file.
        </para>
        <section id='sub:configurations'>
            <title>Configurations</title>
            <para>Dependencies are grouped in configurations. Configurations have a name, a number of other properties,
                and they can extend each other. For examples see: <xref linkend='sec:artifact_configurations'/>.
                If you use the Java plugin, Gradle adds a number of pre-defined configurations to your build. The
                plugin also assigns configurations to tasks. See <xref linkend='sec:java_plugin_and_dependency_management'/>
                for details. Of course you can add your add custom configurations on top of that. There are many use cases
                for custom configurations. This is very handy for example for adding dependencies not needed for
                building or testing your software (e.g. additional JDBC drivers to be shipped with your distribution).
                The configurations are managed by a <literal>configurations</literal> object. The closure you pass to
                the configurations object is applied against its API. To learn more about this API have a look at
                <apilink class='org.gradle.api.artifacts.ConfigurationContainer'/>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:module_dependencies'>
            <title>Module dependencies</title>
            <para>Module dependencies are the most common dependencies. They correspond to a dependency in an external
                repository.
            </para>
            <sample id="moduleDependencies" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Module dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="module-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
            <para>Gradle provides different notations for module dependencies. There is a string notation and
                a map notation. A module dependency has an API which allows for further configuration. Have a look at
                <apilink class='org.gradle.api.artifacts.ExternalModuleDependency'/> to learn all about the API.
                This API provides properties and configuration methods. Via the string notation you can define a subset
                the properties. With the map notation you can define all properties. To have access to the complete API,
                either with the map or with the string notation, you can assign a single dependency to a configuration
                together with a closure.
            </para>
            <para>If you declare a module dependency, Gradle looks for a corresponding module descriptor file (<literal>pom.xml</literal> or
                <literal>ivy.xml</literal>) in the repositories. If such a module descriptor file exists, it is parsed and the artifacts of
                this module (e.g. <literal>hibernate-3.0.5.jar</literal>) as well as its dependencies (e.g. cglib) are downloaded. If no such
                module descriptor file exists, Gradle looks for a file called <literal>hibernate-3.0.5.jar</literal> to retrieve. In Maven
                a module can only have one and only one artifact. In Gradle and Ivy a module can have multiple artifacts.
                Each artifact can have a different set of dependencies.
            </para>
            <section id='ssub:artifact_dependencies'>
                <title>Artifact only notation</title>
                <para>As said above, if no module descriptor file can be found, Gradle by default
                    downloads a jar with the name of the module. But sometimes, even if the repository contains module descriptors,  you want to download only the artifact jar, without
                    the dependencies.
                    <footnote>
                        <para>Gradle supports partial multiproject builds (see<xref linkend='multi_project_builds'/>).
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                    And sometimes you want to download a zip from a repository, that does not have module descriptors.
                    Gradle provides an <emphasis>artifact only</emphasis> notation for those use cases - simply prefix the extension that you want to be downloaded with <literal>'@'</literal> sign:
                    <sample id="artifactOnly" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Artifact only notation">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="artifact-only"/>
                    </sample>
                    An artifact only notation creates a module dependency which downloads only the artifact file with
                    the specified extension. Existing module descriptors are ignored.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section id='ssub:classifiers'>
                <title>Classifiers</title>
                <para>The Maven dependency management has the notion of classifiers.
                    <footnote>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url='http://www.sonatype.com/books/maven-book/reference/pom-relationships-sect-project-relationships.html'/>
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                    Gradle supports this. To retrieve classified dependencies from a maven repository you can write:
                </para>
                <sample id="classifier" dir="userguide/artifacts/excludesAndClassifiers" title="Dependency with classifier">
                        <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="classifier"/>
                </sample>
                <para>As you can see in the example, classifiers can be used together with setting
                an explicit extension (artifact only notation).</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:client_module_dependencies'>
            <title>Client module dependencies</title>
            <para>Client module dependencies enable you to declare <emphasis>transitive</emphasis>
                dependencies directly in your build script. They are a replacement for a module descriptor XML file in
                an external repository.
            </para>
            <sample id="client-modules" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Client module dependencies - transitive dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="client-modules"/>
            </sample>
            <para>This declares a dependency of your project on Groovy. Groovy itself has dependencies. But Gradle does
                not look for an XML descriptor to figure them out but gets the information from the build file. The
                dependencies of a client module can be normal module dependencies or artifact dependencies or another
                client module. Have also a look at the API documentation: <apilink class='org.gradle.api.artifacts.ClientModule'/>
            </para>
            <para>In the current release client modules have one limitation. Let's say your project is a library and
                you want this library to be uploaded to your company's Maven or Ivy repository. Gradle uploads the
                jars of your project to the company repository together with the XML descriptor file of the dependencies.
                If you use client modules the dependency declaration in the XML descriptor file is not correct. We will
                improve this in a future release of Gradle.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:project_dependencies'>
            <title>Project dependencies</title>
            <para>Gradle distinguishes between external dependencies and dependencies on projects which are part of the
                same multi-project build. For the latter you can declare <firstterm>Project Dependencies</firstterm>.
            </para>
            <sample id="project-dependencies" dir="java/multiproject/api" title="Project dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="project-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
            <para>For more information see the API documentation for <apilink class="org.gradle.api.artifacts.ProjectDependency"/>
            </para>
            <para>Multi-project builds are discussed in <xref linkend='multi_project_builds'/>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>File dependencies</title>
            <para>File dependencies allow you to directly add a set of files to a configuration, without first adding
                them to a repository. This can be useful if you cannot, or do not want to, place certain files in a
                repository. Or if you do not want to use any repositories at all for storing your dependencies.
            </para>
            <para>To add some files as a dependency for a configuration, you simply pass a
                <link linkend="sec:file_collections">file collection</link> as a dependency:</para>
            <sample id="file-dependencies" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="File dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="file-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
            <para>File dependencies are not included in the published dependency descriptor for your project.
                However, file dependencies are included in transitive project dependencies within the same build.
                This means they cannot be used outside the current build, but they can be used with the same build.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can declare which tasks produce the files for a file dependency. You might do this when, for example,
                the files are generated by the build.
            </para>
            <sample id="generatedFileDependencies" dir="userguide/artifacts/generatedFileDependencies" title="Generated file dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="generated-file-dependencies"/>
                <output args="-q list"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Gradle API Dependency</title>
            <para>You can declare a dependency on the API of the current version of Gradle by using the
                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.artifacts.dsl.DependencyHandler" method="gradleApi"/> method. This is
                useful when you are developing custom Gradle tasks or plugins.</para>
            <sample id="gradle-api-dependencies" dir="java/multiproject/buildSrc" title="Gradle API dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="gradle-api-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:exclude_transitive_dependencies'>
            <title>Excluding transitive dependencies</title>
            <para>You can exclude a <emphasis>transitive</emphasis> dependency either by configuration or by dependency:
            </para>
            <sample id="exclude-dependencies" dir="userguide/artifacts/excludesAndClassifiers" title="Excluding transitive dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="exclude-dependencies"/>
            </sample>
            <para>If you define
                an exclude for a particular configuration, the excluded transitive dependency will be filtered for all
                dependencies when resolving this configuration or any inheriting configuration.
                If you want to exclude a transitive dependency from all your
                configurations you can use the Groovy spread-dot operator to express this in a concise way, as shown in the example.
                When defining an exclude, you can
                specify either only the organization or only the module name or both.
                Have also a look at the API documentation of <apilink class="org.gradle.api.artifacts.Dependency"/> and
                <apilink class="org.gradle.api.artifacts.Configuration"/>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Optional attributes</title>
            <para id="para:dependencies_with_empty_attributes">All attributes for a dependency are optional, except the name. It depends on the repository type,
                which information is need for actually finding the dependencies in the repository.
                See <xref linkend='sec:repositories'/>. If you work for example with Maven repositories, you need to define the
                group, name and version. If you work with filesystem repositories you might only need the name or the name
                and the version.
            </para>
            <sample id="dependenciesWithEmptyAttributes" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Optional attributes of dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="dependencies-with-empty-attributes"/>
            </sample>
            <para id="para:notation_collections">You can also assign collections or arrays of dependency notations to a configuration:
            </para>
            <sample id="listGrouping" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Collections and arrays of dependencies">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="list-grouping"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section id="sec:dependency_configurations">
            <title>Dependency configurations</title>
            <para>In Gradle a dependency can have different configurations (as your project can have different configurations). If you
            don't specify anything explicitly, Gradle uses the default configuration of the dependency. For dependencies
            from a Maven repository, the default configuration is the only available one anyway. If you work with Ivy repositories and
            want to declare a non-default configuration for your dependency you have to use the map notation and declare:
            </para>
            <sample id="dependencyConfigurations" dir="userguide/artifacts/externalDependencies" title="Dependency configurations">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="dependency-configurations"/>
            </sample>
            <para>To do the same for project dependencies you need to declare:</para>
            <sample id="dependencyConfigurationsProjects" dir="/java/multiproject/services/webservice"  title="Dependency configurations for project">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="dependency-configurations"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Dependency reports</title>
            <para>You can generate dependency reports from the command line (see <xref linkend="para:commandline_dependency_report"/>).
                With the help of the Project report plugin (see <xref linkend="project_reports_plugin"/>) such a report can be created by your build.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Working with dependencies</title>
        <para>For the examples below we have the following dependencies setup:</para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingSetup" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Configuration.copy">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="setup"/>
        </sample>
        <para>The dependencies have the following transitive dependencies:</para>
        <para>shark-1.0 -> seal-2.0, tuna-1.0</para>
        <para>orca-1.0 -> seal-1.0</para>
        <para>tuna-1.0 -> herring-1.0</para>
        <para>You can use the configuration to access the declared dependencies or a subset of those:
        </para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingDependencies" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Accessing declared dependencies">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="dependencies"/>
            <output args="-q dependencies"/>
        </sample>
        <para><code>dependencies</code> returns only the dependencies belonging explicitly to the configuration.
            <code>allDependencies</code> includes the dependencies from extended
            configurations.
        </para>
        <para>To get the library files of the configuration dependencies you can do:
        </para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingAllFiles" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Configuration.files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="allFiles"/>
            <output args="-q allFiles"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Sometimes you want the library files of a subset of the configuration dependencies (e.g. of a single dependency).
        </para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingFiles" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Configuration.files with spec">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="files"/>
            <output args="-q files"/>
        </sample>
        <para>The <code>Configuration.files</code> method always retrieves all artifacts of the <emphasis>whole</emphasis> configuration. It
        then filters the retrieved files by specified dpendencies. As you can see in the example, transitive dependencies are included.
        </para>
        <para>You can also copy a configuration. You can optionally specify that only a subset of dependencies from the orginal configuration
            should be copied. The copying methods come in two flavors. The <code>copy</code> method copies only the dependencies belonging
            explicitly to the configuration. The <code>copyRecursive</code> methode copies all the dependencies, including the dependencies from extended
            configurations.
        </para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingCopy" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Configuration.copy">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy"/>
             <output args="-q copy"/>
        </sample>
        <para>It is important to note that the returned files of the copied configuration
            are often but not always the same than the returned files of the dependency subset of the original configuration.
            In case of version conflicts between
            dependencies of the subset and dependencies not belonging to the subset the resolve result might be different.</para>
        <sample id="configurationHandlingCopyVsFiles" dir="userguide/artifacts/configurationHandling" title="Configuration.copy vs. Configuration.files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copyVsFiles"/>
             <output args="-q copyVsFiles"/>
        </sample>
        <para>In the example above, <code>orca</code> has a dependency on <code>seal-1.0</code> whereas
            <code>shark</code> has a dependency on <code>seal-2.0</code>. The original configuration has therefore a version
            conflict which is resolved to the newer <code>seal-2.0</code> version. The <code>files</code> method therefore
            returns <code>seal-2.0</code> as a transitive dependency of <code>orca</code>. The copied configuration only has <code>orca</code>
            as a dependency and therefore there is no version conflict and <code>seal-1.0</code> is returned as a transitive
            dependency.
        </para>
        <para>Once a configuration is resolved it is immutable. Changing its state or the state of one of its dependencies
            will cause an exception. You can always copy a resolved configuration. The copied configuration is in the unresolved
            state and can be freshly resolved.
        </para>
        <para>To learn more about the API of the configuration class see the API documentation:
            <apilink class='org.gradle.api.artifacts.Configuration'/>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id='sec:repositories'>
        <title>Repositories</title>
        <section id='sub:introduction'>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>The Gradle repository management, based on Apache Ivy, gives you have a lot of freedom
                regarding the repository layout and the retrieval policies. Additionally Gradle provides a couple of convenience
                method to add preconfigured repositories.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:maven_repo'>
            <title>Maven repositories</title>
            <para>To add the central Maven2 repository (<ulink url='http://repo1.maven.org/maven2'/>) simply
                type:
            </para>
            <sample id="mavenCentral" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Adding central Maven repository">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="maven-central"/>
            </sample>
            <para>Now Gradle looks for your dependencies in this repository.
            </para>
            <para>Quite often certain jars are not in the official Maven repository for licensing reasons (e.g. JTA),
                but its POMs are.
            </para>
            <sample id="mavenCentralJarRepo" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Adding many Maven repositories">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="maven-central-jar-repo"/>
            </sample>
            <para>Gradle looks first in the central Maven repository for the POM and the JAR. If the JAR can't be
                found there, its looks for it in the other repositories.
            </para>
            <para>For adding a custom Maven repository you can say:
            </para>
            <sample id="mavenLikeRepo" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Adding custom Maven repository">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="maven-like-repo"/>
            </sample>
            <para>To declare additional repositories to look for jars (like above in the example
                for the central Maven repository), you can say:
            </para>
            <sample id="mavenLikeRepoWithJarRepo" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Adding additional Maven repositories for JAR files">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="maven-like-repo-with-jar-repo"/>
            </sample>
            <para>The first URL is used to look for POMs and JARs. The subsequent URLs are used to look for JARs.
            </para>
            <section>
            	<title>Accessing password protected Maven repositories</title>
            	<para>To access a password protected Maven repository (basic authentication) you need to use one of Ivy features:</para>
    	        <sample id="mavenPasswordProtectedRepo" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Accessing password protected Maven repository">
	                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="maven-password-protected-repo"/>
        	    </sample>
        	    <para>Host name should not include <literal>"http://"</literal> prefix. It is advisable to keep your login and password in <filename>gradle.properties</filename> rather than directly in the build file.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id='sec:flat_dir_resolver'>
            <title>Flat directory resolver</title>
            <para>If you want to use a (flat) filesytem directory as a repository, simply type:
            </para>
            <sample id="flatDirMulti" dir="userguide/artifacts/defineRepository" title="Flat repository resolver">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="flat-dir-multi"/>
            </sample>
            <para>This adds repositories which look into one or more directories for finding dependencies. If you only
                work with flat directory resolvers you don't need to set all attributes of a dependency.
                See <xref linkend='para:dependencies_with_empty_attributes'/>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>More about preconfigured repositories</title>
            <para>The methods above for creating preconfigured repositories share some common behavior. For all of them, defining
                a name for the repository is optional. If no name is defined a default name is calculated, depending on the
                type of the repository. You might want to assign a name, if you want to access the declared repository. For example
                if you want to use it also for uploading your project artifacts. An explicit name might also be helpful when
                studying the debug output.
            </para>
            <para>The values passed as arguments to the repository methods can be of any type, not just String. The value
                that is actually used, is the <code>toString</code> result of the argument object.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:cache'>
            <title>Cache</title>
            <para>When Gradle downloads dependencies from remote repositories it stores them in a local cache located at
                <literal>USER_HOME/.gradle/cache</literal>. When Gradle downloads dependencies from one of its
                predefined local resolvers (e.g. Flat Directory resolver), the cache is not used as an intermediate
                storage for dependency artifacts. The cache is always used for caching module descriptors.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='sub:more_about_ivy_resolvers'>
            <title>More about Ivy resolvers</title>
            <para>Gradle, thanks to Ivy under its hood, is extremely flexible regarding repositories:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>There are many options for the protocol to communicate with the repository (e.g. filesystem,
                        http, ssh, ...)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Each repository can have its own layout.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Let's say, you declare a dependency on the
                <literal>junit:junit:3.8.2</literal> library.
                Now how does Gradle find it in the repositories? Somehow the dependency information has to be mapped to a
                path. In contrast to Maven, where this path is fixed, with Gradle you can define a pattern that defines
                what the path will look like. Here are some examples:
                <footnote>
                    <para>At
                        <ulink url='http://ant.apache.org/ivy/history/latest-milestone/concept.html'/>
                        you can learn more about ivy patterns.
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
// Maven2 layout (if a repository is marked as Maven2 compatible, the organization (group) is split into subfolders according to the dots.)
someroot/[organisation]/[module]/[revision]/[module]-[revision].[ext]

// Typical layout for an ivy repository (the organization is not split into subfolder)
someroot/[organisation]/[module]/[revision]/[type]s/[artifact].[ext]

// Simple layout (the organization is not used, no nested folders.)
someroot/[artifact]-[revision].[ext]
]]></programlisting>
            <para>To add any kind of repository (you can pretty easy write your own ones) you can do:
            </para>
            <sample id="fileSystemResolver" dir="userguide/artifacts/excludesAndClassifiers" title="Definition of a custom repository">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="file-system-resolver"/>
            </sample>
            <para>An overview of which Resolvers are offered by Ivy and thus also by Gradle can be found
                <ulink url='http://ant.apache.org/ivy/history/latest-milestone/settings/resolvers.html'>here</ulink>. With
                Gradle you just don't configure them via XML but directly via their API.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id='sec:strategies_of_transitive_dependency_management'>
        <title>Strategies for transitive dependency management</title>
        <para>Many projects rely on the <ulink url='http://repo1.maven.org/maven2'>Maven2 repository</ulink>. This is not
            without problems.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The IBibilio repository can be down or has a very long response time.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <literal>pom.xml</literal>'s of many projects have wrong information (as one example, the POM of
                    <literal>commons-httpclient-3.0</literal> declares JUnit as a runtime dependency).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>For many projects there is not one right set of dependencies (as more or less imposed by the
                    <literal>pom</literal>
                    format).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If your project relies on the IBibilio repository you are likely to need an additional custom repository,
            because:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>You might need dependencies that are not uploaded to IBibilio yet.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You want to deal properly with wrong metadata in a IBibilio <literal>pom.xml</literal>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You don't want to expose people who want to build your project, to the
                    downtimes or sometimes very long response times of IBibilio.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>It is not a big deal to set-up a custom repository.
            <footnote>
                <para>If you want to shield your project from the downtimes of IBibilio things get more complicated. You
                    probably want to set-up a repository proxy for this. In an enterprise environment this is rather
                    common. For an open source project it looks like overkill.
                </para>
            </footnote>
            But it can be tedious, to keep it up to date. For a new version, you have always to create the new XML
            descriptor and the directories. And your custom repository is another infrastructure element which might
            have downtimes and needs to be updated. To enable historical builds, you need to keep all the past
            libraries and you need a backup. It is another layer of indirection. Another source of information
            you have to lookup. All this is not really a big deal but in its sum it has an impact. Repository Manager like
            Artifactory or Nexus make this easier. But for example open source projects don't usually have a host for those products.
        </para>
        <para>This is a reason why some projects prefer to store their libraries in their version control system. This
            approach is fully supported by Gradle. The libraries can be stored in a flat directory without any XML module
            descriptor files.  Yet Gradle offers complete transitive dependency management. You can use either client module
            dependencies to express the dependency relations, or artifact dependencies in case a first level dependency has no
            transitive dependencies. People can check out such a project from svn and have everything necessary to build it.
        </para>
        <para>If you are working with a distributed version control system like Git you probably don't want to
        use the version control system to store libraries as people check out the whole history. But even here the flexibility
        of Gradle can make your life easier. For example you can use a shared flat directory without XML descriptors and
        yet you can have full transitive dependency management as described above.</para>
        <para>You could also have a mixed strategy. If your main concern is bad metadata in the <literal>pom.xml</literal> and maintaining
            custom XML descriptors,
            <emphasis>Client Modules</emphasis>
            offer an alternative. But you can of course still use Maven2 repo and your custom repository as a
            repository for
            <emphasis>jars only</emphasis>
            and still enjoy
            <emphasis>transitive</emphasis>
            dependency management. Or you can only provide client modules for POMs with bad metadata. For the
            jars and the correct POMs you still use the remote repository.
        </para>
        <section id='sub:implicit_transitive_dependencies'>
            <title>Implicit transitive dependencies</title>
            <para>There is another way to deal with transitive dependencies
                <emphasis>without</emphasis>
                XML descriptor files. You can do this with Gradle, but we don't recommend it. We mention it for the sake
                of completeness and comparison with other build tools.
            </para>
            <para>The trick is to use only artifact dependencies and group them in lists. That way you have somehow
                expressed, what are your first level dependencies and what are transitive dependencies (see
                <xref linkend="para:notation_collections"/>).
                But the draw-back is, that for the Gradle dependency management all dependencies are considered first level dependencies. The
                dependency reports don't show your real dependency graph and the
                <literal>compile</literal>
                task uses all dependencies, not just the first level dependencies. All in all, your build is less
                maintainable and reliable than it could be when using client modules. And you don't gain anything.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
