<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="tutorial_gradle_command_line">
    <title>Using the Gradle Command-Line</title>
    <para>This chapter introduces the basics of the Gradle command-line. You run a build using the
        <command>gradle</command> command, which you have already seen this in action in previous chapters.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Executing multiple tasks</title>
        <para>You can execute multiple tasks in a single build by listing each of the tasks on the command-line. For example,
            the command <userinput>gradle compile test</userinput> will execute the <literal>compile</literal> and
            <literal>test</literal> tasks. Gradle will execute the tasks in the order that they are listed on the
            command-line, and will also execute the dependencies for each task. Each task is executed once only,
            regardless of why it is included in the build: whether it was specified on the command-line, or it a
            dependency of another task, or both. Let's look at an example:</para>
        <sample id="multipleTasksFromCommandLine" dir="userguide/tutorial/multipleTasksFromCommandLine">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Below is the result of executing <userinput>gradle -q libs test</userinput> for this build script. Notice that
            the <literal>compile</literal> task is executed once, even though it is a dependency of both
            <literal>libs</literal> and <literal>test</literal>.</para>
        <sample id="multipleTasksFromCommandLine" dir="userguide/tutorial/multipleTasksFromCommandLine">
            <output args="-q libs test"/>
        </sample>
        <para>Because each task is executed once only, executing <userinput>gradle libs libs</userinput> is exactly the same
        as executing <userinput>gradle libs</userinput>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Selecting which build to execute</title>
        <para>When you run the <command>gradle</command> command, it looks for a build file in the current directory.
            You can use the <option>-b</option> option to select another build file. For example:
        </para>
        <screen>
> gradle -b subproject/build.gradle
        </screen>
        <para>Alternatively, you can use the <option>-p</option> option to specify the project directory to use:</para>
        <screen>
> gradle -p subproject
        </screen>
    </section>
    
    <para>You can find out more about the <command>gradle</command> command's usage in <xref linkend="gradle_command_line"/></para>
</chapter>